Issues and Mitigation Strategies when using Agile Industrial Software Development Processes in Student Software Engineering Projects

Abstract— In computer science education, one of the main goals for educators is to prepare the student for employment in an industrial environment. For this it is required that the students are familiar with the major development process, ideally on the example of a concrete student project. During a one-semester software development seminar the students were grouped into 7 groups with 4-5 students each and each group was assigned eXtreme Programming, SCRUM or Open Unified Process as development process. Each student was asked to keep a development diary and answer questionnaires during and at the end of the project. Each group was asked to document the changes to their development process, identified development problems, employed mitigation strategies and the project progress in form of a retrospective report. Analysis of the reports revealed common issues and mitigation strategies, which can be classified into the following: meeting organization; communication; project roles, requirements engineering, continuous tests and process adherence. The employed mitigation strategies were classified into the same categories; quantified and evaluated regarding their respective effectiveness.

Keywords: education; development process; student exercises; process tailoring

I. INTRODUCTION
The critical and conscious use of standard industrial software development processes is an essential skill for every computer science graduate. To teach a deep understanding of software development processes, the usual approach is to define a small project; assign students into small groups (typical: 5 – 7 students / group) and assign an industrial software development process. While this approach can be used to teach basics about the specifics of a certain development process, it may be not entirely possible for the students to follow this process due to the restrictions imposed by the university environment and due to their lack of experience.
Student groups usually have a different setup, than typical office based development teams. The key differences are: there is no common work schedule; there are no common office locations and many students have other day-to-day responsibilities (e.g. jobs). These differences make a daily interaction between all student members almost impossible.
The higher the group size, the higher is the communication and organizational overhead for the development group. Therefore physical inter-student communications tend to drop during the programming courses, which leads to a highly component oriented development process where each student only develops his or her component. At the end of the course, these components are then integrated causing the usual problems of Big Bang integrations.
Many of the currently employed quasi standard agile development processes like eXtreme Programing (XP), SCRUM require a high level of daily inter-developer interaction [1], [2]. Examples for these required interactions are daily meetings (e.g. Standup Meetings in XP or SCRUM) and pair programming [2]. These interactions are essential for a successful industrial project since they facilitate information exchange between the developers and introduce a certain level of transparency into the development process, which allows the project manager to accurately evaluate the development progress [3].
To evaluate the acceptance and suitability of agile industrial software development processes for student groups we performed a study during the course “Software Engineering Seminar” which is aimed at early “Software Engineering & Internet Computing” master students. The goal was to receive feedback about common occurring issues and used workarounds when utilizing an off-the-shelf software development process.

II. METHOD
The difficulty when evaluating a software development process is the gathering of accurate data. Evaluating such a process in an industrial software development environment with a narrow spatial distribution of all development team members, which are all available at a certain time at a specific location several times a week is straight forward since gathering of data is possible in multiple ways e.g. by observing the teams or by regular interviews. This is not possible with student groups. Student groups seldom work together at the same location at the same time. To evaluate the development process of student groups, we applied the following methods:
Questionnaires: Similar to [4] questionnaires were used to receive information about the status of the teams, their development process and to increase the process awareness of the team members. Questionnaires were completed by the students 1.5 and three months after the start of the course. Tables I and II show the questions for both questionnaires. Questionnaire 1 was used at both questionnaire phases, questionnaire 2 only in the last.
Student Diary: The students were asked to keep a diary about their individual experiences with this project. The diaries focus on the personal experience with the development process and the project progress.
Final report: Each group was asked to create a report about the project and the software process. The aim of the report was to facilitate a retrospective of the entire development process and the adaption to the university environment. This report highlights the chosen process and compares the commitments made at the beginning to how the process was actually implemented. It further includes the perceived advantages and disadvantages of the process, the difficulties that stem from the university environment, the project history (e.g. burn-down charts) and the results of the project (e.g. mock-ups, screenshots).
Group Discussion: The student groups were asked to give two presentations about their project during the course (1.5 months after the course start and at the end of the course). These presentations had to include a presentation of the original textbook process, their adaptation and the implementation progress.
The quality of the report artifacts depend on the honesty and openness of the students. To assure student cooperation we established that the main focus of the lecture is the evaluation of the process, the quality and accuracy of the reports and feedback about implementing the process in a student environment.
The quality of the application itself and whether the group adhered to the original process were therefore not part of the grading.
The questionnaires and the reports were evaluated at the end of the course. Based on the diaries and reports, common occurring problems and their respective mitigation strategies were then categorized into main problem and workaround categories.
The application itself was only loosely specified with five core functionalities and a draft for the data model. This required the students to employ a requirements engineering process and to simulate the customer.

Table III shows the final group configuration for the course.

TABLE I. QUESTIONNAIRE 1
Question
Which sotware development process did you choose?
How many students are in your group
Does your process require fixed roles? Which are they? Does your process require an iterative development with a release after each iteration?
Explain how you learned the process and what sources you used.
How hard for you was it to understand the process?
How hard for you was it to setup the process?
How hard for you was it to follow the process?
Did you adapt the process so far? If yes explain.
What communication paths did you establish?
Which kind of meetings do you hold?
Are these meetings defined by the process? Explain. What degree of cross functionality would you assign your project?
Explain the technical framework for your solution.
Explain your requirements engineering process?
How clear are the requirements at the begin of an iteration? Do your requirements change during an iteration? If yes: why?
Which tools do you use to support your process?
What kind of tools do you miss for an optimized process support?
What degree of parallelism would you assign your development process / team?
TABLE II. QUESTIONNAIRE 2
Question
Did you already have experience with your chosen technology?
Were you satisfied with your technology choice? Explain
Were you satisfied with the process? Explain.
Explain your actual development process. Did you use Pair Programming? Explain.
How do think will the experiences gained in this project influence your future projects?
Did you create a project plan? If not: Why? If yes: what information did you use as a basis? How often did you change the plan? Did the plan represen reality? Was it an usable planing tool?
Based on your previous experience and based on the experience from this project: How would you describe an optimal process?
Answer
SCRUM, XP, OUP
1 - 5
Free Text Free Text
Free Text
1 (easy) – 5 (hard)
1 (easy) – 5 (hard)
1 (easy) – 5 (hard)
Free Text Free Text Free Text Free Text
1 (low) – 5 (high) Free Text Free Text Free Text Free Text
Free Text Free Text
1 (low) – 5 (high)
Answer
Yes / No
Yes / No, Free Text
Yes / No, Free Text
Free Text
Yes / No, Free Text
Free Text
Yes / No, Free Text
Free Text
TABLE III.
FINAL GROUP CONFIGURATION
                                                      Development Process
SCRUM
SCRUM
SCRUM
eXtreme Programming eXtreme Programming eXtreme Programming Open Unified Process Total
Number of students
    5 5 4 4 4 4 4 30

A somewhat similar approach as been used in a report by Tan et al. [5]. The main difference is, that Tan et al. use a four-semester course to create the environment for a more detailed project. They further actively perform the user role, and therefore are key to the requirements project. To receive more objective results from the students, the authors of this paper avoided active participation in the project.

III. RESULTS
The reported issues and mitigation strategies can be classified into the following categories.

1) Identified Issues
Meeting Organization: Arranging meetings with all team members was a problem for every team and hence, every team resorted to video or chat conferences. This was attributed to the university environment and the fact that all team members had multiple liabilities (jobs, other courses).
Communication: All teams found it difficult to communicate efficiently. Despite the use of newsgroups, Skype, e-mail and other communication tools it was not possible to establish an effective direct communication between the team members. This was most problematic when a specific person needed to be contacted but was unreachable. The issue is caused by the typical spatial distribution of student group members. Internet based communication was perceived as ineffective and cumbersome compared to direct face-to-face communication.
Project Roles: The roles could not be assigned as defined by the process because of the small team size. Therefore, some team members were assigned multiple roles. The role of the customer, which due to the lack of concrete requirements at the project start, was perceived as a critical role. One SCRUM team rotated the Product Owner/Customer role. One SCRUM defined and prioritized their user stories as a group effort. The other groups assigned the customer role as a second role to a developer.
Requirements Engineering: Requirements engineering did not cause any issues. But requirements prioritization was troublesome for all teams with a customer role. Only three SCRUM groups employed a designated requirements management tool (Agilo and Atlassian Jira/Greenhopper). The other groups chose a simple text based approach (Microsoft Excel and/or a Wiki).
Continuous tests: Tests were performed at the end of each iteration by the OUP team, one SCRUM team and two XP teams. One SCRUM team applied test-driven development (TDD) and reached a test coverage of over 90%. One XP team did manual tests and automated these at the end of the project. One SCRUM team did not implement sufficient integration tests, this lead to additional bug fixing effort at the end of the project.
Process adherence: The teams found it difficult to adhere to all aspects of the original textbook process due to the small team size and the multiple roles some team members had to take over. This imprecise utilization of the chosen development process was not identified as an issue per se, but many of the reported development issues can be attributed to on-the-fly changes to the process when needed. Due to the lack of the students’ practical development experience, these
changes may introduce additional issues for the groups. Combined with poor communication one SCRUM team split up into two separate teams where each team had a different responsibility. One XP team did not adhere to the XP standards as it reasoned that the project was not complex enough to justify the effort. The other two XP teams found the XP practices helpful. One SCRUM team did resort to a small waterfall model during the course since they did not completely understand the process. The third SCRUM team only had to perform minimal changes. In this team, all members also worked together in the same company, and therefore were able to perform the necessary meetings at their workplace. The OUP team followed the process to the letter despite its challenging demands for documentation. Due to the distribution of team members no team fully implemented all required meetings of their assigned process. All teams employed an iteration length of either one or two weeks.
Another key aspect in agile development processes is pair programming. In [6] Sherrell and Robertson conclude that agile software development with pair programming is well received by the students. In this study however, the aspect of pair programming is not entirely seen as useful. Two XP teams found pair programming helpful, one XP team found, that pair programming led to ineffective coding sessions. Since many of the pair programming sessions were done at the students’ place, it was hard for the students to focus at the task at hand. The other groups did not implement pair programming at all.
Many problems can be attributed to the lack of communication and the low number of team members. Because of that, no team fully adhered to their chosen process. The students accepted the given limitations and used the university environment as an excuse for not being able to implement the process. There were no reports of actually improving the process during the course. When asked, none of the student had improvement suggestions.

2) Issue Mitigation Strategies
To overcome the issues presented in the previous section, the students employed various workarounds.
Meeting Organization: Except for one SCRUM team all SCRUM and XP teams, which development process requires a daily meeting decided to employ much looser schedule, resulting in one to three meetings per week.
Communication: To overcome arising communication issues, all teams employed Internet based voice communication (Skype). In addition three teams used a mailing list with an archive function for group communication.
Project Roles: The only role, which was mentioned as missing by the student groups, was the designated customer role. One SCRUM team rotated the customer role inside the project team. This led to constant change in the task prioritization and was not perceived as a good solution. Five groups reported a customer who was also assigned a developer role. In these groups the customer was only half-heartedly implemented, which in turn led to unclear requirements and task prioritization at the begin of an iteration.
Requirements Engineering: The lack of concrete requirements at the project start, forced the students to manage their requirements themselves. Missing tool-support was never mentioned as an issue. The team, which used a collaborative approach for managing their requirements did not report any issues with this method and created stable and useful requirements throughout the project.
Continuous Tests: Since the quality of the application was not part of the grade, no group fully implemented a structured state-of-the art test process. Even the group who employed TDD in the beginning continued a strict TDD process only half-heartedly.

IV. CONCLUSION
The nature of student development groups and their respective environment prohibits a “by the book” implementation of industrial software development processes. The difficulty for the teacher is to tailor the process to the particularities of student software development groups while maintaining and conveying the important parts that are essential in industrial software engineering projects. One way to tackle this is to include organizational communication strategies, like using Internet-based communication instead of daily face-to-face meetings, when assigning software development processes to student groups. Since many of these students lack practical industrial experience, they may run into unnecessary problems when trying to tailor these processes to their respective team. Providing an already tailored process also increases the inter group comparability which is necessary for an accurate grading system. Similar results have been found in the publication by Robillard et al. Robillard et al. conclude, that students with little or no practical experience yield better results with an already structured process [7]. The problems when following an agile process like XP or SCRUM in this study are similar to the findings in [8]. Bunse et al. conclude, that the lack of guidance and experience in agile projects cause lack of quality and usability in the resulting software. In this study, even though the software quality was not part of the evaluation, we could observe the same issues in the resulting application.

V. DISCUSSION
Due to the limited sample size with seven project groups and a total of 30 students, this study only presents an indication of typical issues in student software development groups when using a standard software development process. Another limitation due to this initial character of the study is the focusing on student groups of only one university.
These two limitations will be addressed in further studies. The results however suggest a set of core issues, which occur
in all of the student groups and therefore present valid points to address in university software development course.

