Agile Implementation- A milestone for Academics using Software Engineering Industry Practices

   Abstract— Agile methods are getting popular in project development. When it comes to software engineering techniques, the methodology is to be selected according to the requirements of the software being developed or the project in consideration. There is always a question as how well a technique implemented in industry can be effectively be applied in academics also to train students as if in industry. This paper aims to increase the understanding of how pair programming and scrum can be adopted in academia. A case study approach using 12 university students, supplemented with feedback form, ethical forms on pair programming in academia. The methodology for pair programming was performed in the university lab. The Scrum approach was performed in a Group projects for national level. We proposed two frameworks SIA and SEAM that uses the industry practiced models with the focus on pair programming and scrum in academics. Thus we propose two novel models named Scrum in Academia (SIA) and Software Engineering Agile Model (SEAM) in Academics while students engage in group projects as a team to get quality work to be submitted meeting deadline as if in industry. We argue that the approach of using pair programming and scrum methodology can be adopted in the academics.

Keywords— Agile Methodology, Scrum, Extreme Programming, Pair Programming, Academics, SEAM, SIA.

I. INTRODUCTION
When the development of software can be done in small incremental planned pattern, it is referred as an agile technique. The technique to be adopted for the same depends on the kind or type of software that is developed. To an extent this depends on the purpose, scope and time span given for the project in consideration. To understand agile concepts better we have concentrated our research into pair programming and scrum.
In pair programming we have experimented from a previously developed framework by Lipsa et al. [12]. While the Scrum was utilized to learn and understand effective teamwork for Industry and National level projects by students. Thus we propose two novel models named Scrum in Academia (SIA) and Software Engineering Agile Model (SEAM) in Academics while students engage in group projects as a team to get quality work to be submitted meeting deadline as if in industry.
Effectively we argue that the model SEAM has a set of attributes that one should have as a Software Engineer. These attributes of SEAM are applied to SIA to effectively use agile patterns in Academia.
Section I is the introduction itself, Section II is a description on the Agile Methodologies, Section III is a discussion on the agile practices in the industry, Section IV is agile practiced in academics with pair programming experimented and rated, Section V is the description of the framework SEAM, Section VI is the framework SIA described and Section VII is the conclusion with future works on how these can be experimented in academics.



VI. PROPOSED FRAMEWORK 1-SEAM
The framework, Fig. 2 SEAM (Software Engineering Agile Method) has four key factors that determines the framework components.
Our Model SEAM (Software Engineering Agile Method) targets all the attributes of academics. The proposed model can be further implemented in SIA. Addressing the four factor below:

A. Target system
1) Software architecture
The software architecture (Bass et al.) [13] of a program or computing system is the structure or structures of the system, which comprise software elements, the externally visible properties of those elements, and the relationships among them.
The Structure of any system depends how a team is divided and organized. The group decides on what system and management to adopt and focuses on its own missions and deadlines. The team goes through the part of Scheduling, test plans, interaction and configuration. For example the team leader provides different access permission for different groups and required to finish testing for their production before the whole system is tested. The groups acquire many experiences after performing several projects. The developer becomes expertise at their own area and supports the team. For example the developers who understand the user’s habit maybe good in developing GUI or who configures database may do well in the making of database. The only factor the group suffers through is architecture changes due to software architecture [14].
2) Functional Requirement
Functional Requirements are those which give an idea of a product software. The features and the characteristics of the software are described. These requirements can also include what the product should not contain [15].
3) Non-functional Requirements
Non-Functional Requirements [16] are the necessities that don’t appear in use cases. They are concerned about how the application will provide the required usefulness. There are three distinct areas in non-functional requirements:
a) Technical Constraints: They oblige design choices by specifying certain technologies that the applications must utilize. “We only have Java developers, so we must develop in Java”.
b) Business Constraints: These constraints are not technical related but only business for example “The supplier of our middleware has raised prices prohibitively, so we’re moving to an open source version”.
c) Quality Attributes: These characterizes an application requirements regarding availability, scalability, portability, convenience, execution so on. These attributes matter a lot to application users and other stakeholders like project team or sponsors. Therefore Architects have to understand functional requirements and simultaneously also fulfil the non-functional requirements.

B. Institutional Values
1) Meet all syllabus requirement
The first priority of any educational institution is meeting requirements of their curriculum. The educational institution can be university where the student needs to complete all the required credits to achieve a degree in a professional course.
2) IT infrastructure
All the required Technological Infrastructure is expected to be provided by the University to enhance the project requirements. This should include advanced versions of software’s, hardware’s, faculty guidance etc.

C. Students
The language and communication skills helps the student understand the project criteria’s. It is a way to express their emotions, ideas. It benefits you to work well with other students. It impacts their achievements. It is mandatory for the students participating in the team to have good technical knowledge about the domain that the project belongs to. This enables easy communication within the team. Students experience with minor projects though all semesters in that curriculum should be added advantage for better time management, leadership quality a resolving problems with confidence. Networking with students and professor develops professional skills that is vital for student career. Maturity is another factor where when students working in teams view things in different perspective and have an experience of the real world.
D. Academics
Even though the project is of a practical nature, a strict pedagogy is expected to be followed which is comparable to industry standards. Students are expected to follow all guidelines of curriculum requirements to achieve their learning and subject outcomes. Therefore the model gives a lot of importance to the learning aspect as well.


VII. PROPOSED FRAMEWORK 2- SIA
The second framework SIA (Scrum in Academics) proposed in Fig. 3 is expected to implement SEAM model throughout the project. The figure is a modification for academics from the general SCRUM pattern used in industry projects.
Thus the components of SIA are the following while implementing in an external project that the industry seeks from the students to work as a team. This shows the effect of how a product can be experimented, developed and evaluated by external evaluators as if by customers in industry practices.

A. External Evaluator
When a project is in its working state, external evaluators are its stake holders.
In SIA we refer this evaluator as the party to whom the project is submitted for a competition or as a research product.

B. Student Team
The students who work in the project are the scrum team members who we argue to have all the qualities that the model SEAM talks about. They can be divided into smaller groups of 2 or 3. These team members are expected to work and update on the progress of the project to the faculty supervisor on a regular basis according to scrum requirements.

C. Supervisor/Mentor
They provide guidance and 3 c’s: confidence, courage and coaching. They are responsible to teach the team to deal whenever each time a new complex problem arises. The nature of Software engineering is itself complex and can only be resolved through hard work, intelligence [17]. Academics supervisor should be referred as the faculty guide who is marking students for the project. The faculty guide is expected to follow scrum rules implemented in terms of student daily reporting and review. The scrum master leads the scrum project.

D. Product Backlog
The entire requirements of the project is the Product Backlog which is the wish list. This is very well understood by the faculty supervisor and explained to, students so that they decide on the timelines and their capacity to work on the project. While considering the requirements, the first concern is about the deadlines to be met for each sprint and the final product delivery.

E. Sprint Planning Meeting and Sprint Backlog
Students split into teams at this stage and pick those requirements which can be met at the earliest. The sprint should be planned by the students along with faculty supervisor in such a way that at the end of each sprint a workable module of the project is developed and delivered to be updated with the external evaluator. After each sprint such deliverables are expected from the student teams.

F. Daily Stand up Meetings
On a daily basis students are supposed to meet their faculty guide who is their scrum master for a quick stand up meeting for about 10 or 15 minutes. These meetings evaluate the progress and discuss the flaws and success, suggestions and grievances that students may have during their project work.

G. Sprint Review
At the end of every sprint which may be held from 1- 4 weeks’ time, a review is performed to deliver finished modules to the external evaluator. This review can be beneficial where the faculty guide can evaluate how fast teams were in delivering the functional requirements and sprint backlog.

H. Finished Project and Sprint Retrospective:
This is the last stage, of the SIA where students are up with their finished backlogs of the project. That is a completely deliverable product submitted to the external evaluator. This includes finished product along with product documentation.
A sprint retrospective evaluates how good the project went and what are the future scope of the project. This is a good forum to evaluate student capability individually and as a team.


VIII. CONCLUSION AND FUTURE WORKS
Software engineering can be developed further than the industry level. In this paper, we explored how pair programming and agile technique can be implemented in academics. The paper proposes two novel models SEAM and SIA and an experiment on Pair Programming to research if all the practices can be implemented at a university level. The Pair Programming proved to be very successful and guaranteed that it would help the student in industry career.
Our future works are definitely to experiment the SEAM and SIA frameworks for group projects to be submitted for industry level competitions and record their significance to make this a complete practice to be adopted in academics.



 from the 1)
2) 3) 4) 5)
were positive. Hence, the result concludes that pair
students who worked in pair programming.
Your ability to think while your colleague works on code,
Your ability to switch and write the codes,
Your ability to work as a pair with your colleague, Speed of programming,
Sharing of ideas and concepts.
The feedbacks for pair programming from over 12 students












