Agile Transformation for Capstone Projects: Preparing Graduates for the Job Market

Abstract—Preparing graduates for the job market is a key objective of higher education. The Information Technology (IT) department at King Saud University has adopted a strategy of program alignment with industry to ensure that program outcomes are in line with the market needs and requirements. Graduates in the field of Information Technology should be equipped with software development skills needed by industry to drive business value and deliver high quality software products and services. To this end, the IT department undertook the decision to adopt an agile transformation strategy for the final year capstone project course converting it from a waterfall software development process model to an agile approach in response to the job market need. In this paper, we present the transformation strategy, the design of the course, and discuss opportunities and challenges. Reporting our transformation experience will provide insights and guidance to those who want to undergo a similar transformation.

Index Terms—Capstone Project, Agile Transformation, Scrum, Software Development Method, Software Engineering Education


I. INTRODUCTION
University education is a higher-level education that focuses on high-level skills. It is a key enabler for the economic growth and development of countries. An important outcome of university education is preparing graduates for the job market and increasing their employability. This is achieved by continuously aligning the programs the university offers with industry needs and requirements. Universities incorporate this by offering new programs that target key areas needed in the industry and by improving existing programs using feedback from industry partners and employers. Specifically, for university degrees offered in the information technology domain, this need is more apparent as the graduate skills needed by employers are changing rapidly.
For the bachelor’s program in Information Technology offered by the Information Technology (IT) Department at King Saud University (KSU) in Riyadh, Saudi Arabia, program alignment with industry has been a priority. The IT department has endorsed a strategy of curriculum review and development that addresses the need for program alignment with industry. The IT department periodically reviews the program in light of technological advancements in the field and the changes it brings to industry. Recently, the IT department redesigned the bachelors IT program by introducing new current tracks, with new courses [1].
This year, the department has focused on revitalizing the capstone project course (the final year project), making it an opportunity for students to engage in industry-like practices by adopting agile methodologies for the software development process. Since the inception of the IT program, the approach that has been adopted for the capstone project software development was the traditional waterfall model. The waterfall software development process model is a popular standard for the development of specific kinds of software products such as embedded systems, real-time systems, and safety-critical systems. Although this approach is very well known and established in the software engineering industry, it is not the ideal approach for capstone projects. Capstone projects are usually experimental in nature, testing new ideas and novel solutions, thus, the requirements cannot all be explicit and well defined at the beginning of the project, which is a requirement for software products developed using the waterfall approach.
To align with industry need, and increase the employability of program graduates, the IT department made the decision to adopt an agile approach for the software development in the capstone course. Since the Agile manifesto was published in 2001 [2], agile approaches such as Scrum, Extreme Programming, Feature-Driven Development (FDD), and Dynamic Systems Development Method (DSDM), among others, gained popularity over the years. Today, agile approaches are mainstream in industry among software engineering practitioners [3]. A popular framework for agile software development is Scrum [4], a recent annual report on the state of agile shows that Scrum and related variants continue to be the most common Agile methodologies used by respondents’ organizations [3]. Scrum is an adaptive, iterative, fast, flexible, and effective framework. It gained popularity as it allows for fast delivery of products and services providing significant value for business, lower risk of failure, and high level of customer satisfaction. Therefore, in the software development job market, employers are constantly seeking candidates who are skilled in agile approaches including the Scrum framework. The Scrum framework was chosen as it is the most popular in industry practice. In this article, we present the agile transformation journey for the capstone project in the IT department at KSU. Even though it is still an ongoing journey, we present here the agile transformation methodology and the design of the capstone course. We also discuss challenges and opportunities when adopting agile for software development in an educational and learning context.


III. COURSE DESIGN
A. Agile Transformation Planning
Any transformation should start with planning. In the two semesters preceding the agile transformation start date, a strategic plan was developed which sets a vision, a mission, and a number of objectives as follows.
Vision: Graduates who are in alignment with the needs of the Saudi IT job market.
Mission: Adopting agile methods to improve the process of graduation projects software development and delivery.
Objectives:
1) General:
a) Develop a seamless sustainable approach to an agile software development for the capstone projects at the IT department.
b) Identify key metrics to measure the success of agile transformation for the graduation projects.
c) Create a central repository accessible by faculty and students that contains all materials relevant to capstone projects (guides/ handbooks/ recorded seminars and workshops, links to tools, etc.).
d) Formulate agile transformation teams necessary to realize the agile transformation strategy.
2) Process:
a) Identify key roles and responsibilities for capstone projects courses (teaching and administration) within an agile framework (Scrum).
b) Develop capstone projects process using the Scrum framework.
c) Review and update current policies and procedures, milestones and deliverables, schedules, handbooks, templates and guides.
d) Review assessment strategy for capstone projects including rubrics and evaluation forms.
3) Software Tools and Training:
a) Communicate with college industry partners to identify suitable tools for agile development using Scrum, and review the training options available for faculty and students.
b) Select and setup software tools required for agile software development and delivery.
c) Prepare training material for faculty and students on agile methodology, the Scrum framework, and capstone projects process and policies.
d) Conduct workshops for faculty and students on agile methodology, the Scrum framework, and capstone projects process and policies.
e) Prepare training material for faculty and students on software tools students should use for agile software development at the IT department.
The cornerstone for any successful agile transformation is awareness and knowledge, therefore, the first stage of the capstone project agile transformation included conducting a number of workshops and seminars at the beginning of the semester. The objective of these workshops and seminars was to share with faculty and students the agile transformation strategy, including the motivation and objectives. In addition, workshops were also conducted to explain agile methods, specifically, the Scrum framework, and the tools to be used.

B. Scrum Implementation
We aim to revitalize the capstone project course by adopting an agile methodology for the software development process. To achieve this goal, we implement a variation of a well-known agile method: Scrum. Even though the Scrum roles and practices are slightly modified in our course, the overall structure of Scrum is closely followed. Before the course starts, students organize themselves into small teams (3-4 students each). Then each team is assigned a project idea and a supervisor (an IT faculty member). The project assignment process takes into account the students’ preferences and their GPAs. This year, we have 23 graduation projects in various domains.
1) Scrum Roles: The major roles of Scrum were modified according to our context. The Product Owner is the project supervisor, the Developers are the undergraduate students, and the Scrum Master is a faculty member from the Scrum Master Team. The Scrum Master Team consists of three IT faculty members. Each Scrum Master is responsible for 7-8 capstone projects.
2) Scrum Ceremonies: We ask all teams to practice four key Scrum ceremonies: Sprint Planning, Daily Scrums, Sprint Reviews, Sprint Retrospective. Each team is asked to conduct 15 minutes daily meetings to review and discuss the task progress. We have three pre-scheduled Sprint Reviews in each semester. Each Sprint Review occurs after the sprint increment submission. The objective of each review is to examine the work done and obtain feedback from the Product Owner. The team should discuss how the developed increment pass the acceptance tests and any improvements the Product Owner may suggest. Sprint Retrospectives allow teams to reflect on what occurred during each sprint. For example, identifying problems that may affect team productivity and discuss solutions to those problems. We plan to have three Sprint Retrospective meetings, one at the end of each sprint. The Scrum Master Team is in charge of monitoring the effective adoption of those events.

C. Course Organization
The course is organized into four phases: proposal, Sprint 0, Sprints 1-5, and final submission. Each phase has different outcomes and deliverables.
1) Project proposal: On the first week, each team needs to prepare a project proposal describing the problem, the solution, the product, and the Scrum team. The product description involves providing details about the product vision, product roadmap, objectives, scope, and a list of hardware and software they plan to use and their costs. The proposals are reviewed by the capstone projects Examination Committee. The committee either approves the proposal or asks the team to resubmit after revision. By the end of the second week, all teams will receive feedback.
2) Sprint 0: For the first sprint, students are asked to do preliminary work: understanding the problem domain, requirements collection and elicitation, setting up the development environment, and designing the overall system architecture. The main deliverable of this sprint is the first chapter of the project report which contains the Introduction, Background, Literature review, System description (users, architecture, use case diagram), Definition of Done, and the Product Backlog. Sprint 0 is the only sprint that is three weeks long.
3) Sprints 1-5: Every subsequent sprint is a short development cycle in which the team creates a shippable product.
During each sprint, the team is expected to go through the following key agile development phases: lightweight analysis and design, implementation, sprint-level integration (for the sprint user stories), increment-level integration (current with previous increment), and testing. Three types of testing are required in each sprint: unit, user acceptance, and integration testing. Testing the non-functional requirements (as provided in the Definition of Done) is carried out during the last sprint.	
All sprints are four weeks long with one week between sprints to allow for Sprint Review and next Sprint Planning. The sprint diagrams, test cases, and integration steps form the next chapter of the project report.
4) Project final submission: At the end of each semester, students are asked to present their work and demonstrate their releases to the Examination Committee.

D. Tools
To support the efficient implementation of Scrum and to get the students acquainted with the project management tools used in industrial settings, we require students to use tools that are popular among practitioners and support the agile practices. These tools include:
Jira Software1: Each team creates a Scrum team-managed project in Jira that is used for creating the Product Backlog and filling it with user stories, creating the Sprints and their Sprint Backlog and tracking progress through Scrum board and Sprint burndown chart.
Atlassian Confluence:2 Students use Confluence to document their weekly meetings with their supervisor (Product Owners), Sprint reviews and Sprint retrospectives. Moreover, students use Confluence to organize, and collaborate on any documents produced during the project.
GitHub3: Students in each team keep their work synchronized by creating a GihHub repository for hosting code files.

E. Introducing and Controlling Scrum Work
Before the start date of each sprint, students are given a seminar that covers the main activities involved in the sprint. Moreover, students are given a guide that explains the sprint main activities, outcomes, and deliverables. Students are also provided a sprint template to help document the sprint chapter.

F. Course Evaluation
The course evaluation is based on students’ progress (assessed by the supervisor), the final product (assessed by the capstone projects Examination Committee), and the way they implemented Scrum (assessed by the Scrum Master). The three evaluations are worth 50%, 40%, and 10% respectively. The supervisor evaluates the students’ weekly progress based on several criteria including commitment, productivity, quality of work, critical thinking, creativity, communication skills, and time management. The supervisor is expected to base their assessment based on the weekly meetings with the students and the Sprint Reviews.
Each team submits two software releases at the end of each semester. Each release is submitted to the capstone projects Examination Committee who assess each project on the basis of the number and quality of user stories accomplished from the Product Backlog, the fulfillment of releases and sprint plans, the quality and completeness of the software documentation developed (project report), and the quality of the project presentation. The Scrum Master assigned to each team assesses the way students implemented Scrum during the development of the product such as maintenance of the Product Backlog and Sprint Backlog and meeting of deadlines.



1 https://www.atlassian.com/software/jira
2 ttps://www.atlassian.com/software/confluence 3 https://github.com


IV. DISCUSSION
The agile transformation has not been a simple task, given that people are usually reluctant to change and are not comfortable with it especially if it involves more effort and work. However, initial feedback from faculty and students shows that they are adapting to the change, and with the support and guidance the department is providing, the adoption process has shown no obstacles or hurdles so far.
A noticeable challenge was that capstone projects belong to different categories of systems; web-based systems, mobile applications, IoT based systems, and data science projects. This difference made it challenging to have a unique and conferment style for reporting and evaluation of each sprint outcome. For data science projects which require data collection and preparation and model training, it was challenging for students to produce a shippable product increment at the end of each sprint cycle.
Although faculty and students were enthusiastic about the transformation and change, they did have queries. This was addressed by providing help and support through various channels: the Scrum Masters support, the capstone project clinic, and the capstone course coordinators.
One of the challenges faced by the transformation team is the review and adaptation of the capstone project report, rubrics and evaluation forms to reflect the new process. Students need to be graded now on the successful application of Scrum, in addition to producing working product increments after every sprint.
As we are in the middle of this transformation process, it is still an ongoing journey and we are learning from our experiences and adapting as we go to fulfil our mission and achieve our vision for the agile transformation of capstone projects at the IT department in KSU.


V. CONCLUSION AND FUTURE WORK
In this paper, we presented the design of the agile transformation strategy adopted by the IT department at King Saud University for the final year capstone project course. The transformation was from the traditional waterfall software development process to an agile approach using the Scrum framework. We also presented challenges and opportunities
and provided insights for those wishing to do a similar transformation.
In future work, we plan to report the comprehensive experience including results and feedback from faculty and students regrading this transformation. Specifically, we plan to conduct surveys after the end of each semester in order to evaluate the transformation process and quality. The goal is to identify students and faculty perceptions of the overall transformation and detect where improvements can be made. In our case, three types of surveys are needed, one for students, one for faculty, and one for the Examination Committee. The student evaluation survey aims to measure the students overall learning experience. The faculty evaluation survey aims to measure the overall supervising experience. The Examination Committee evaluation survey aims to measure the overall quality of the developed projects.
