Teaching Agile Software Development at University Level: Values, Management, and Craftsmanship

Abstract
Agile methodologies have come a long way over the last decade. Several recent surveys show that agile methodologies like Scrum, Extreme Programming have been successfully adopted by many companies to develop their software. However, the same surveys show that only few of the agile practices are used and even fewer are applied consequently and thoroughly. This is to a great extent due to the lack of skilled personnel. Although teaching agile software development has drawn some attention in recent research and has been discussed in several papers, we do not yet seem to be able to “deliver” the appropriately skilled personnel. What is the reason for this, and more importantly, how can we improve the situation? In this paper we propose a more holistic approach for teaching agile software development, in which the required agile practices and values are not only integrated theoretically into our courses but also practically applied and repeated until they become a habit to our graduates. The proposed concept was realized in a new Software Engineering course held at Zurich University of Applied Sciences during 2012. The evaluation shows very encouraging results, but also leaves some challenges and problems to be solved.

1. Introduction
Recent surveys [1], [2] show that agile methodologies in many respects deliver better outcomes than plan-driven ones. As a result, agile software development has been adopted by many IT companies and IT departments. In the Swiss Agile Study (SAS) [2], a survey conducted by the authors, these findings have been confirmed. More than half of the participating companies are using an agile methodology like Scrum [14] or XP [15] – Agile has become mainstream!
Unfortunately, this also has a significant impact on the agile team constitution. The early adopters of agile approaches were all highly mature and technically skilled experts in their fields. They had internalized the agile philosophy, were very productive and produced high quality results. Today’s agile teams, however, are “normal” software teams, with architects, seniors and juniors in one team, and many of them are not yet familiar with the agile philosophy. Even though those teams have improved in software development to some extent, they are far less productive than the early adopter expert teams. Survey results show that quality has partially even gone down and overall costs increased. One reason for this is that many of the important agile practices are not applied as thoroughly [2] as the agile pioneers proposed.
In this paper we will analyze the situation on the industry side in more detail to find out, which skills are missing and make a proposal how education on university level can help to improve this. We will suggest a holistic teaching approach, which integrates the necessary agile engineering and managements skills together with the core agile values, into the education of agile software development.
In section 2 we will give an overview of related work to set our paper in context. In section 3 we will analyze the reasons for the rather poor performance of today’s agile teams and contrast this with the current state of software development education. In section 4 we will present the Agile Competence Pyramid as a model for the required competences for agile software development. In section 5 we will present the layout of a new Software Engineering course, which was held at the Zurich University of Applied Sciences in the 5th semester of the undergraduate Computer Science program. Section 6 contains the evaluation of the first execution of the course followed by suggestions for implementation. We conclude with an outlook on further work.

3. Motivation
The SAS shows, that there are too few software engineers with the skills for agile development. This suggests that we as teachers do not yet educate the students with the required skills. This assumption is backed by answers in Table 2.

Table 3: Agile as part the computer science curriculum
     Items Completely Disagree disagree
Agile development should be an integral part of the 0% 5% Computer Science curriculum
Agile should not be taught at university, it is better 34% 48% learned on the job
Agree Completely agree
49% 46% 12% 7%

Table 3 answers the questions, whether agile development should be an integral part of the computer science curriculum. The vast majority of the participants recommend that agile software development should be an integral part of the computer science curriculum. As educators, we have to take the findings from the above tables seriously and try to make sure that future graduates will have sufficient knowledge of agile methodologies.

3.2. Evaluation of Effort and Learning Effect
Two major characteristics of agile software development are its focus on working software over documentation and lightweight management. Therefore, the authors wanted to know how much effort the students spent on programming, management and documentation in the lectures and in the student projects, and about the learning effect they got from these activities. Table 4 and Table 5 summarize the results of the evaluation which 103 students filled in.
Table 4: How do you estimate the effort for the different activities?
              Far too high
Too high
Exactly right
Too little
Far too little
        Lecture
Project
Documentation 4% Management 2% Programming 4% Documentation 32% Management 18% Programming 2%
25% 36% 23% 12% 16% 45% 27% 11% 9% 50% 27% 10%
38% 27% 3% 1% 31% 40% 10% 1%
8% 40% 34% 16%

Table 4 shows that the students estimated the effort spent for the different activities in the lectures more or less appropriate. In the student project, however, the majority of the students estimated the effort spent for documentation and management too high or even far too high.
Table 5 shows that the students estimated the learning effect of management activities significantly higher in student projects than in lectures. Interesting is the result for the documentation activity. The learning effect for software project documentation was seen to be much lower in the student project than in lectures. Setting this in relation to the results from Table 4 might suggest that the wrong style of documentation was taught in the student project.

Table 5: How do you estimate the learning effect?
    Very high
 High
 Low
 Very low
                 Lecture
Project
Documentation Management Programming Documentation Management Programming
0% 22%
2% 29% 18% 45% 8% 29% 10% 39% 18% 42%
47% 31% 51% 18% 24% 14% 51% 12% 38% 13% 28% 12%

The perceived results of this evaluation support the authors’ hypothesis, that too much time is spent on agile management practices and, even worse, on documentation. The strong focus on documentation might come from the still existing influence of plan-driven methodologies.


5. Agile Software Engineering Course
The course was a typical 16-week semester class in the last year of the undergraduate level (B.Sc.). The students completed one Java programming project in an agile team of six to eight members during the course of the semester. Per week there were a 2 hours lecture with the whole class and a 2 hours programming workshop with half the class. 27 students were enrolled.
The scope of the course was equivalent to four ECTS credit points (European Credit Transfer and Accumulation System). One credit point is equivalent to 30 hours of studying; the total was therefore 120 hours. Table 6 shows the distribution of lectures, workshops and self- study:

Table 6: Distribution of lectures, workshops and self-study
     Lectures Workshops Self-study Total
32 h 32 h 56 h 120 h

“To say that Scrum and XP can be fruitfully combined is not really a controversial statement. “ [16].
The authors have successfully used a Scrum-XP-hybrid for many years and therefore decided to use it in this course as well. Why do Scrum and XP work well together? Scrum focuses on management practices while XP focuses mostly on engineering practices – they address different areas and complement each other.

5.1. Layout of the New Software Engineering Course
Table 7 shows the layout of the course. The course was divided into two parts of equal length and was designed with the insights from the previous chapters in mind. The two parts reflect the competence pyramid in Figure 1. Part one (week 1 to 7) lays the focus on building a strong foundation, i.e. the engineering practices. Part two (week 8 to 14) builds the second layer of the pyramid, i.e. the management practices. Both engineering- and management practices were actively applied in a student project during part two.

Table 7: Overview of semester plan
   Lecture
 Workshop
 Week
1 eXtreme Programming Agile Manifesto
2 eXtreme Programming Version Control
3 eXtreme Programming Project Automation
4 Continuous Integration
5 Unit Testing
6 Unit Testing / Mock Objects
Clean Code / Code Smells
7 Refactoring
8 Introduction to Test-Driven Design / Scrum
9 Scrum
10 Scrum
11 Agile Estimating and Planning
12 Metrics Agile Teams
13 User Stories Agile Principles
14 Demonstration of computer games
15/16 Preparation for examination:
No lecture
Installation IDE and Plug-Ins Coding Assessment 1
Coding Assessment 2
Version Control System (SVN) Build Scripts (Ant)
CI (Jenkins Build Server) JUnit
JUnit
EasyMock
Refactoring
TDD, The Craftsman articles
Agile Game Development (Sprint 1) Agile Game Development (Sprint 2) Agile Game Development (Sprint 3) Planning Poker
Agile Game Development (Sprint 4) Metrics (EMMA)
Agile Game Development (Sprint 5)
Agile Game Development (Sprint 6) Preparation for examination:
No workshop


For this course, the following learning target was defined using Bloom’s taxonomy [19]:
“After successfully attending this course, students have the necessary skills to develop software in an agile team. They can apply the most important agile engineering- and management practices and understand the importance of the agile values.”

5.2. Part One: Applying Engineering Practices
eXtreme Programming (XP) In the first two lectures the students were given an introduction to XP. The XP practices and the Agile Manifesto were discussed. In the workshops, each student completed a coding assessment and was given feedback.
Version Control. As a preparation for Continuous Integration, the concept of a version control system (VCS) was introduced. Subversion (SVN) [23] was used as repository in the workshop. Some students suggested that GIT should rather be used than Subversion.
Project Automation. Ant (Another neat tool) [20] build scripts were introduced in the lecture and practiced in the workshops. Some students suggested using Maven instead of Ant build scripts.
Continuous Integration. (CI) With version control and project automation in place, the concept and benefits of CI were discussed. In the workshop, a CI-server Jenkins [21] was configured.
Clean Code and Code Smells. Clean code [9], [10] has had a marvelous effect on the quality and readability of student’s code. The students read most of the Clean Code book [9] as part of the self-study.
Unit Testing and Mock Objects. The concept of automatic unit testing was introduced. In the workshop, exercises with JUnit and EasyMock were carried out. These JUnit tests were added to the CI-server.
Refactoring. Good understanding of automatic unit testing and refactoring are the basis of Test-Driven Design. A catalog of refactorings was discussed and practiced in the workshop.
Introduction to Test-Driven Design (TDD). “TDD is hard. It takes a while for a programmer to get it.“ [17]. TDD is especially difficult to teach in the classroom. For that reason, the students were only given an introduction to TDD. In the workshop, the students worked through some of the craftsman articles [18]. One student gave the following feedback: “Reading the craftsman articles really helped me to understand how TDD works.”

5.3. Part Two: Applying Management Practices
Student project. While the students were working individually or in small groups in part one, part two was different - the agile game was played in the classroom.
In order to really understand how Scrum works, the students must be members of a “real” Scrum team. Since this is not possible in the classroom, the Scrum team was simulated in the student project.
The goal of the student project was to develop a 2D computer game applying all needed engineering practices. The students worked in four Scrum teams of six to eight. Each team was free to decide what kind of computer game they wanted to develop. One student was voted ScrumMaster; the lecturer was the product owner. The teams completed six one-week sprints. Every week during the workshops, each team did the sprint planning, sprint review and retrospective coached by the lecturer. During self-study, the students developed the actual game. In the last week, all the teams could demonstrate a working game. In order to get a good start, the students were given an introduction to game development with Slick2D [22].
Scrum was introduced in the lecture. Problems and questions, which had arisen in the Scrum teams where addressed in the next lecture and discussed in the plenum.
Pair Programming was introduced ad hoc. The students were asked to pair with peers while developing the game.
Planning Poker. Agile estimating and planning [11] was introduced during the lecture and practiced in the Scrum teams. User stories [12] were estimated by playing planning poker.
Task board. The functioning of the task board and burndown charts were discussed. For this course, an electronic task board was used.

5.4. Teaching Agile Values
Agile values [13] are difficult to teach. The approach in this course was to show the students, that these values are not just something the creators of the Agile Manifesto intended to give lip service to and then forget. They are working values. The concepts of agile values were introduced in the first part. Usage of the values was propagated in the second iteration through means like retrospectives, common code ownership or pair programming. Many discussions during the lectures and workshops tried to transport that message.

6. Evaluation
6.1. Student Feedback
In the last week of the semester, 24 students filled in an evaluation form (the items and answers are translated from German). An excerpt of the encouraging results is shown below.
Table 8: Course evaluation
The content of this course is... 12 11
This course was divided into engineering- 12 11 and management practices and agile values.
How would you judge this concept?
How did the agile values come across in the 1 19 lectures and workshops?
In the student project, you worked in a 9 11 Scrum team of 6 to 8 fellow students. How
would you judge this concept?
How would you judge the workshops in part 1 20 one?
How would you judge the workshops in part 6 14 two?
Table 9: How did you like the course?
0 0 0 0
1 0 4 0
1 0 3 0
  Items
 Excellent
 Good
 Bad
 Very bad
                                              Items
 Yes
 No
     Would you recommend this course to your fellow students? 231 Did you enjoy this course? 200

In the planning phase there was some uncertainty as to whether the student project would falter due to group size and commitment of the individual member of the scrum teams. These fears were ungrounded. On the contrary, the students were exceptionally committed and delivered top quality computer games. The students were asked what they liked most about the course. Following are some statements, translated from German:

Table 10: What did you like best about the course?
“... the development of the computer game in a Scrum team”.
“... that the material in the course was not only covered theoretically but I also had the opportunity to apply and deepen it in the workshops”.
“... the practical relevance”.
“... that the topics covered were interesting and important. I had the opportunity to practice the newly learned in the student project. That was great!”
The students were also asked what they disliked about the course. Nine students did not have any dislikes. Most of the students disliked the amount of work during the student project in the second part. Many students suggested that the student project should be longer (see Table 11).

Table 11: What did you dislike about the course?
“... too much work during the second part”.
“... too little time for developing the computer game”.
“... agile was praised too much. Negative aspects of agile were not or too little mentioned”. “... the electronic task board”.
“... too little time for the student project, because of simultaneous projects in other courses”.

6.2 Evaluation of Learning Outcomes
The quality of the students’ work was measured twofold. On the one hand, the student project presentations, which included a demonstration of their computer games, were evaluated. On the other hand, the students had to pass a formal oral exam. The average grade was a 5.1 on a scale from 1 (very poor) to 6 (excellent). This was higher than expected. A systematic classification of the outcome quality remains to be done.

7. Suggestions for Implementation
The experience from this course and input from students lead to the following suggestions:
Group dynamics are very important and therefore special attention should be paid to the way the Scrum teams are put together. The students should have access to a room, where they can meet for standups and have a wall for the task board. For this course, an electronic task board was used. Unfortunately, because of poor performance it did not meet our expectations.
Working only a couple of hours every week on the student project is not ideal. Many students suggested an intensive week instead. During this week, the students would only work on the project in the Scrum team. One semester is rather short for the material covered in this course. If the students had been familiar with engineering practices like unit testing, refactoring, build automation or clean code prior to the course, this time could have been used for test-driven development or additional iterations.

9. Summary
Agile software development processes have gained great popularity in industry over the last years. However, the Swiss Agile Study shows that the full potential of agile methodologies is not yet used.
In 2012, a Software Engineering course was taught at Zurich University of Applied Sciences, which was designed to address this problem. In this course, the students applied agile engineering- and management practices and special attention was paid to agile values. In Scrum teams of six to eight students, computer games were developed while strengthening the students’ agile software development skills. An evaluation shows that the concept of this course was well received, and that participants learned a great deal about agile methodologies while having fun.