Focusing on both Teaching Agile Software Development and Communication

Abstract – The field of Software engineering haves several roles, one of their important roles is communication. It has been found that communication helps with a better understanding of the product the stakeholder needs to be developed. If software engineers can understand and be able to express their understanding to the stakeholders or to their team half of the problems would be solved. This would lead to better utilization of resources. Thus, for educating students for the future, this study focuses on teaching agile development to students with an emphasis on communication. This study is ongoing, and the presented research includes one year of data. The same process is repeated this year.

Keywords- software engineering, communication, Agile software development, writing, presentations

I. INTRODUCTION
While problem solving ability is considered important, communication is one of the key factors for not just a successful engineer but also for a successful project. Braham in [1] says how engineers working for any project cannot act independently. They will have to work with different people from different sectors for a project to be successful like lawyers, industrial lawyer etc. Although a lot attention has been paid to software development and its process over a past few years, less attention has been paid to develop a good “Software Engineer” [2]. The key ingredients which topped the list to make a good Software Engineer are problem solving, analytical skills, communication, and professionalism [2]. A survey conducted in [3] showed that communication is the most required soft skill for various software development jobs including jobs for system analyst, designers, programmers and software testers. Similar resulted were seen in [4]. Most of the research talks about communication but that does not just include team and group communication. It includes writing skills, presentation skills, reading, understanding and summarizing skills [5]. Communication does not inly help the team to connect or an individual to grow but also helps to reduce technical ambiguity. For example writing skill which is a part of communication skill is important to write better requirements document in order to reduce ambiguity and inconsistency [6]. Thus, it is important and desirable for a Software Engineer to develop good
communication skills to grow as a professional and for the betterment of the organization.


II. METHODOLOGY
In this study, the focus is in on educating students for the future developing communication skills. The Agile software development course was taught to novice students with several techniques,of which 35% of the grade with focus on communication. Both written and oral communications are used here. Four major communication assignments are discussed in this study. These were used to teach students about agile manifestos, agile framework, user stories, estimation, roles, product prioritizationand a choice of agile testing. The assignments were spread across the whole semester.
To better understand when each of these assignments were assigned to students, the semester is equally split into four quarters.
The first major communication assignment was assigned in the second quarter of their semester. This is 15% of the 35% that they have in the communication group. The motivation of this assignment was that each student learns a detailed concept of any chosen Agile framework. First, they are asked to explain an example that best suits for each of the following processes: extreme programming, feature driven development, Dynamic systems development method, Lean, Kanban and Scrum.
Next, each student had to choose any one process like extreme programming team, feature driven development team, Lean Team, Kanban Team, and Scrum Team. They, then discuss how the process and the application they mentioned fit that chosen process. They must write the whole software development processes for the Agile process they have chosen in three to four pages.
The second major communications assignment was a take-home midterm that was based on Agile manifestos. This assignment was 10% of their 35% of the communication block. This was assigned to them between the second and the third quarters.The following instructions were given to them-
⎯ Read the given journal article [7]
⎯ Apply the agile manifestos to your interest/hobby and detail how you would implement agile manifestos to teach or implement the interest/hobby in question. i.e. develop an agile development instructional framework for your hobby/interest.
⎯ Submit an article not less than five pages in the IEEE format uploaded here.
⎯ Please submit as a word document so I can allow double-blind review
The third assignment was assigned in the third quarter of the semester. It is called the lighting talk assignment. This was 5% of the 35% that was used for the communication block. This was presentation in which they had to prepare 15 slides and had to be timed such that the presentation is completed in five minutes. The slides had to scroll automatically, and they did not have any control over the slides. They had to talk as each of the slides appear. The topic was their choice from a list of agile vocabularies given to them.
The final major communication assignment was assigned to them in the fourth quarter. This was fulfilling their partial requirement of the final exam. The weightage on this assignment was 5% of the 35% communication block. Here they had to write two pages about a topic from the list of topics given. They also had to make a presentation. The following were the instructions given for this assignment. Choose a topic, make a presentation and write about two pages on any topic that you choose from below. Make citations and references if needed. You must write in your own words. To get maximum credit - use examples to explain the topic with the definition and all information. The following are topics that were included – Agile testing, Acceptance criteria, Test Driven Development (TDD), User Stories writing best practices, MoSCoW, DEEP, Level of Effort (LOE) or T-Shirt Sizing, Roles in Scrum


III. RESULTS
The first major assignment helped them think analytically and critically about the agile framework. They got a detailed understanding of that one framework. This understanding will help them apply a framework or a combination of agile framework that suits best for their team project. This assignment will also help them take roles and sides when developing their team project.
The second assignment was also used as a midterm assessment. It firstly, helped them understand agile manifestos. The second helped them to relate to some non-software product that they wanted to develop. Third, helped them learn writing skills so stakeholders and non-technical personals can understand. Finally, they learned to write articles in academic templates.
The third assignment was for them to be able to present. The motivation behind this was to gain confidence and an in-depth understanding of a terminology they choice. Also, to help them present within a given time frame. To get the assignment done, students had to practices the presentation as well as have enough data to fill in the 15 slides they were asked to make. They also realized how they should time themselves so that they can emphasize the core concepts they choose to present.
The motivation behind the final communication assignment was summing up their communication skills and assessing their understanding of the topic they chose.Here most students chose the testing topic. There is no evidence from students as to why they choose the testing topics. It is assumed that since it was the last topic discussed in class, they felt comfortable to choose it. It could also be assumed that they now wanted an in-depth understanding of agile testing piece.


IV. CONCLUSION AND FUTURE WORK
Overall the students appreciated the teaching pattern of using multi-mode approaches. This process needs to be repeat to get a better understanding of the approach. In the future, to help students better write a co-teaching class or a schedule time with the writing center would help students to learn to write. Students can be asked to present their work at the student conference, so they present their work in public. This might help them increase their self-confidence.s