Learning Scrum by doing real-life projects

Abstract— Being Scrum the agile software development framework most commonly used in the software industry, its applicability is attracting great attention to the academia. That is why this topic is quite often included in computer science and related university programs. In this article, we present a course design of a Software Engineering course where an educational framework and an open-source agile project management tool were used to develop real-life projects by undergraduate students. During the course, continuous guidance was given by the teaching staff to facilitate the students' learning of Scrum. Results indicate that students find it easy to use the open-source tool and helpful to apply Scrum to a real-life project. However, the unavailability of the client and conflicts among the team members have negative impact on the realization of projects. The guidance given to students along the course helped identify five common issues faced by students through the learning process.

Keywords—Agile software development; Scrum; agile project management tool; software engineering education

I. INTRODUCTION
Learning Scrum allows university students to improve their technical and non-technical skills (e.g. the ability to solve problems on a fast and efficient way), which leads to obtaining high-end products [8]. The improvement of skills, however, demands the application of different instructional methods. In this direction, the active learning approach along with complementary educational resources and tools are, nowadays, effective means for students to reach the expected learning outcomes [9]-[10].
Regarding the use of tools, previous studies have found that using a Scrum management tool has a positive impact on students when they develop their course projects. A tool facilitates the application and understanding of the fundamental Scrum concepts, giving the trainees the opportunity to implement high-quality solutions [11]. Nonetheless, the use of new methodologies and supporting technologies is not always well-received by students. Although most of them show enthusiasm and put high effort in understanding how the tools support the process, others exhibit a lack of interest, as presented in [12]. In the case of practitioners, a survey reported in [1] indicates that nearly 71% of software developers prefers to use Scrum supporting tools for managing a project as they ease many processes and help saving time.
In this work, we present a course design of a Software Engineering course where an educational framework and an agile project management tool - based on Scrum- were used to develop real-life projects by students. The study is aimed to determine whether the course design helps undergraduate students to learn and correctly apply Scrum.
The rest of the article is structured as follows: section 2 describes related works; section 3 describes the methodology of the study; section 4 presents the results; and section 5 concludes the article.

III. METHODOLOGY
The methodology followed in this study is comprised of three main phases: A) selecting and evaluating an agile project management tool; B) applying an educational framework; and C) guiding students through the learning process.

A. Selecting and evaluating an agile project management tool
In order to select a Scrum-based suitable project management tool, a set of desirable features was defined based on the recommendations of [17]–[20]. These recommendations include: management of sprints, user roles, task prioritization, backlog support, decomposition of user stories into tasks, a virtual task board, tasks estimation and project tracking.
Table I shows the features reviewed for each of the tools. Additionally, we only considered tools with open source licensing due to budget constraints in our university (public) and because students could use them throughout their university program. For identifying proper tools, we looked for the most recommended open Scrum-based planning tools [19]–[21], reviewing their attributes on their websites. Jira and Taiga met all the features we were targeting; nevertheless, we chose Taiga as project management tool as it was not possible to use for free the web app of Jira more than seven days. Taiga provides a dynamic taskboard, which means that it offers the users full control of the user stories; besides, it gives notifications of the state of the tasks and supports the communication among the team members.

TABLE I.
COMPARISON OF OPEN SOURCE SCRUM TOOLS
Agile project management tools
Jira Open Project Agilefant Taiga Orange Scrum Tuleap
 Features
User role management 
User stories management 
Sprints management 
Task prioritization 
Backlog support 
Task creation within user stories 
Virtual task board 
Tasks status notifications 
Communication among team members

To evaluate the selected tool (Taiga), a survey was administered among the participating students. A questionnaire of three sections was designed to get insights about their perceptions regarding: 1) the usefulness of the Taiga tool for learning and applying the Scrum framework; 2) the usability of Taiga; and 3) their adaptability to changes. The last section was neccesary to evaluate whether the students’ adaptability to changes has an effect on their learning process (e.i. learning Scrum by doing, using a tool, developing a real project). The survey was administered twice during the semester, specifically at the 8th and 15th weeks.
The design of the questionnaire was based on the ideas taken from the study conducted by Mahnic [16], with respect to learnability and applicability of Scrum with undergraduate students. In addition, we used and adapted the questions of the SUS (System Usability Scale) questionaire [22]-[23] to evaluate the usability of Taiga. Finally, we customized a measurement tool of resistance to change, available in [24]. We also took into consideration the findings of Gandomani et al. [12] for evaluating whether students registered at the course exhibited some resistance to change.

B. Applying an educational framework
For this phase, we used an educational framework, aimed to make students achieve the expected learning outcomes using a learning by doing approach [25]. Figure 1 shows how this framework was applied in a software engineering course.
As can be observed, the framework has inputs, guidelines and outputs. The inputs refer to the teaching material used during lectures and workshops, as well as the tools required to develop the project. The guidelines focus on: the content to be covered in the agile software development sessions; the intended learning outcome (ILO); the teaching and learning activities (TLA); and assessment tasks (AT), designed to achieve the expected outputs. Finally, the outputs correspond to the project to be developed by students and the learning experience gained during the course.
The framework was applied in a course named Software Engineering II (16 weeks long) during the first academic semester, from May to September, 2016. The topics covered in the course were: agile software development; code standards; testing; code coverage and refactoring. One of the ILOs of this course is to develop a real-world project using mainly focusing on two of its principles: time-boxing and self-organization. Time-boxing deals with managing a project having time constraints, while self-organization has to do with being responsible to perform project tasks without being directed or controlled. A set of TLAs and ATs were designed to achieve this specific ILO; table II shows the corresponding timeline of the activities.
Regarding the activities TLA1 and TLA2, the assigned hours were used to review and reinforce what students had learnt about agile software development and Scrum in a previous course (Software Engineering I). The lecture (TLA1) was oriented to explain the agile manifesto and Scrum; and the workshop (TLA2) was performed to assign the roles to be played by students in the project and to define the product backlog. Scrum meetings of fifteen minutes long were held on each class and a sprint retrospective was held at the end of the sprints.
TLA3 and TLA4 included a short training session and a workshop about Taiga. The objective of TLA3 was to provide a scoop on the functionalities of Taiga to students. During these phases, students were trained about how to use the basic elements of Taiga, perform a sprint planning, assign roles, tasks and corresponding deadlines. Throughout the workshop, the students used Taiga for planning Sprint 1 of their projects. From then on, they had to use Taiga to manage their projects. Along the course, students received continuous feedback from the teacher and the teaching assistant. Another teacher, participating as observer, became involved by giving suggestions to enhance the teaching and learning process, as well as to give ideas about how to conduct activities with the participating students.
In the case of the activity AT1, a quiz of seven questions was designed to test the understanding of Scrum concepts and their application. The questions were based on available Scrum tests [26]-[27], focusing on: the responsibilities per role; scrum activities; documents; backlogs; and meetings. All questions were multiple-choice type, having four possible answers each. For example:
Choose the correct statement about sprint reviews:
A. The sprint review is performed daily.
B. Key stakeholders are invited to attend the sprint review.
C. The sprint review lasts 15 minutes.
D. The retrospective is a review performed at the end of the project.

The quiz was administered three times during the academic term (weeks 4, 8 and 15) in order to evaluate the progress of students' acquisition of knowledge, according to the Scrum framework.
The activity AT2 involved the development of a project in teams of 4 or 5 students. The teams were randomly selected, and each of them was allowed to choose what project to work on for a real client. The software products to be implemented by all the teams were three-tier web applications. In addition, two of the teams also developed an Android-based mobile application. There was no obligation to work on a software project from scratch. That is, if a client asked a team to make some adjustments to an existing system, students had to agree and implement the required changes. The products were the following: a booking system for a lodging house (team 1); a quotation and technical service management system for an air- cooling company (team 2); a shopping cart for a coffee producer company (team 3); an inventory management system for electronic devices of a research lab (team 4); and an app for soccer championships, useful for high school tournaments (team 5). The projects were presented in a fair-type event to the clients and three invited teachers. The latter were asked to test the products for evaluating the extent to which the software package was carried out in compliance with the clients' requirements. As shown in table II, the activity AT2 only considers the time supervised by the teacher during the class sessions.

C. Guiding students through the learning process.
It was the teacher and her assistant's duties to clarify the students’ doubts about the use of Taiga or the right application of Scrum on a weekly basis. This task involved detecting any misunderstanding or errors related to the application of Scrum and use of Taiga. Regarding the application of Scrum, we identified the following students' difficulties: 
doubts about what kind of tasks can be created within each user story; new user stories and tasks created once the sprint had started; tasks not completed at the end of the sprint; task changes (new deadline or person in charge of doing it); and user stories performed without planning. To avoid making the same mistakes, feedback was given to students during the guiding sessions. According to Hattie and Timperley, 2007, feedback is an effective means when giving directions of how to improve a task as well as clarifications of concepts and procedures -not completely understood by students [28].
Concerning the use of Taiga, the problems arised when configuring this tool, including: adding deadlines to tasks; making delegation of tasks; creating roles and management of role permissions. To tackle these difficulties, a short tutorial was created and shared with students. In addition, personalized assistance was given to each Scrum master.
 Six formal reviews were performed along the course to document the observed issues per team. A short report was sent to the scrum masters to make them aware of the problems encountered during the revision session.

IV. RESULTS
This section presents the results of: the survey administered 5
to evaluate Taiga; the Scrum quiz; the level of compliance of requirements for each project; and the issues encountered during the monitoring sessions.
1) Survey
To test the reliability of the instrument, the Cronbach's Alpha test was run for each of the three sections of the survey,
which includes: the application of Scrum using the Taiga tool; 2 the usability of Taiga; and the adaptability of students to changes. As it can be observed, the Cronbach's Alpha value was significantly above the cut-off point (0.7), which indicates that
the instrument has a good internal consistency. When 4 performing this test in both instances of this research study, the Cronbach's Alpha values were all well above 0.7, indicating that
the instrument maintained its consistency in repeated measures.
Considering that the scale used for the survey is of an 2 ordinal type, being 1 "Total disagreement" and 5 "Total agreement", the statistical test was performed by calculating the median of each item, specifically the Mann-Whitney U test. By performing this test, we wanted to determine whether 5 differences exist in the median of the perceptual values given by students at T1 and T2 regarding the three main aspects included in the survey.
With respect to the application of the Scrum methodology while using Taiga, the U statistic resulted no significant at the 0.05 level. This means that the medians for each item in this section, at time T1 and T2, are practically the same. In other words, this result seems to indicate that students do not have difficulties in applying the Scrum's principles using Taiga as the medians are, in general, closer to the highest value.
Similarly, when examining the usability of Taiga, the U statistic was not significant at the 0.05 level; indicating that no differences exist in the medians at time T1 and T2. Accordingly, this result evidences that students value Taiga tool for its usability.
Regarding the questions about the students’ adaptability to changes, the test resulted in no significant differences of the medians at time T1 and T2. This means that students show openness to change and adopt new ways of doing things and using tools. The table IV presents the medians of the items for the three survey sections and the significance values (p). 
In summary, students perceived that Taiga is a tool that allows the application of Scrum concepts to a real-world project. They also perceived that Taiga is a tool relatively easy to use. These results seem to indicate that students are open to change and use new tools in their learning process. Indeed, students commonly use tools for the design, programming and testing tasks during the course of their university programs.
It is important to mention that one survey question asked students to give suggestions about the improvements on Taiga as a tool for managing projects using Scrum. Some of the main suggestions are as follows: to create a quick access to the task board; to show the due dates for each task (easily and clearly); to give the possibility of modifying tasks in few steps; to allow the integration with social networks; and to improve the notifications system (e.g. assigned tasks, upcoming deadlines).
2) Scrum quiz
The Kruskal-Wallis test was performed with the data gather from the Scrum quiz, this was done to verify whether the scores reached by the students on the seven questions of the quiz -in the three instances of the present research study (T0, T1 and T2) are the same.
By running this test, we found that no significant differences exist, at the 0.05 level, in the sum of the right answers to the seven questions of the quiz at the three instances of the study (see Table V). This result provides evidence that the students' acquisition of knowledge and its application, in general, are consistently achieved throughout the academic term. Regardless of this result, the sum of right answers tends to be to some extent higher at time T2 as shown in table V. This may reflect that the guidance provided by teachers and the use of a tool like Taiga for educational purposes help students reinforce the concepts of Scrum reviewed in the software engineering course.
3) The project
As described in section III, part B (applying an educational framework), the client and invited teachers evaluated –before the final exam- the extent to which the software developed by the students met the stated requirements (see Table VI). The level of compliance was evaluated based on the following scale:
(1) The software product does not meet the requirements
(2) The software product functions although some requirements have not been implemented or do not work properly.
(3) All the requirements have been implemented and work properly.
(4) The software product exceeds the expectations, offering more functionalities than requested, which adds value to the client.
As it can be observed, teams 1 and 4 experienced problems and did not get the expected results. In the case of team 1 (working on a booking system for a lodging house), one of the difficulties was that the client was not always available to interact with the students. In addition, the lodging house was located three hours from the university campus, making it hard for the students to get there. The Internet connection with the lodging house was not as good as expected due to the earthquake affecting the coastal zone of Ecuador; therefore, having videoconferences was not possible. Consequently, only few meetings were held with the client.
In the case of team 4 (working on an inventory management system for electronic devices of a research lab), the problem was the lack of interpersonal skills for managing good relationships among the team members. In fact, two students have a strong temperament, the scrum master and one member of the team. Both members exert strong pressure on the other peers to convince them about what task to do and how to do it; hence, usually, no consensus was reached. Due to these differences, several times, some functionalities of the working software product were developed more than once. After the team evaluation, the conflicting member decided to abandon the team. The other students went to a supplementary evaluation and finished the project with success. All the software products, except the one developed by team 1, are currently in use.
4) Guidance given to students
Table VII summarizes the issues found in each of the six formal revisions of the project. We focused our attention in identifying issues related to the two Scrum principles that we wanted students to develop: time-boxing and self-organization. The first column corresponds to the type of issue while the rest contains the frequency of the issues during the review sessions (i.e. number of teams demonstrating a wrong use of a Scrum concept).
The identified issues are as follows:
X Issue 1: New user stories and tasks created once the sprint had started.
x Issue 2: Tasks not completed at the end of the sprint.
x Issue 3: Task changes (new deadline or person in charge of doing it).
x Issue 4: User stories performed without planning
x Issue 5: Problems when configuring the tool

CONCLUSIONS
In this article, we report how we designed a software engineering course by using an educational framework and an agile project management tool to instill in students the learning of Scrum. As discussed, this was not an easy task since a strong commitment from the students, clients and teaching staff was needed to achieve the expected results.
Developing real-world projects in an academic environment presents some challenges. The most critical were the unavailability of the client, the conflicts among the members of a team, the use of Scrum to develop a software product as this is commonly something new for students, the use of a project management tool, and the allocation of a teaching staff to guide and monitor students as a way of giving them support for realizing their projects according to expectations. As previously discussed, the first two have a negative impact on developing the product, while the other challenges are rather manageable and not so difficult to deal with.
According to the statistical tests, no significant differences were found regarding the perception of students about how easy to use Taiga is and how well Scrum concepts are applied. These results seem to indicate that students get rapidly accustomed to use different types of tools for developing software products.
Similarly, the statistical tests performed with the scores reached by the students at each quiz provide some evidence that concepts were relatively well understood right from the beginning. However, the students faced some difficulties when applying Scrum, i.e. having tasks not completed at the end of the sprint. This is not surprising as applying a concept in a real-life situation is not as easy as understanding it.
The results presented in this study give us support to believe that the teaching and learning activities together with the assessment tasks and the fair-type event are advisable and they should be adopted for further courses. Inviting clients and teachers make students realize the importance of developing quality products and making a commitment to accomplish the results as expected. However, the selection of clients needs to be done carefully to avoid having difficulties with unavailability of clients or their organizations located too distant from the university campus.














   Topic: Agile software development
 Core: Scrum
 Content:
Agile manifesto
Scrum
Agile project management tool
  ILO: Develop a real world project using Scrum
 Tools:
• Taiga
• Github
• Google drive
• Programming
tools
Teaching material:
• Slides
• Books
• Websites
  TABLE II.
Activities TLA1: Lecture
TLA2: Workshop (Scrum: roles, product backlog, sprint backlog) TLA3: Short training (Taiga planning tool)
TLA4: Workshop (using Taiga for planning a sprint)
AT1: Short quizzes about Scrum AT2: Team project
TLA1: Lecture (Agile manifesto & Scrum) TLA2: Workshop (Scrum: roles, product backlog, sprint backlog)
TLA3: Short training (agile project management tool)
TLA4: Workshop (using Taiga for planning)
 TIMELINE OF THE ACTIVITIES
When
week 2 week 2
week 3
week 3
weeks 4, 8 & 15 weeks 3 to 16
Time (hours)
1 1.5
1
1.5
1 28
Feedback to students
 Fig. 1. Application of an educational framework, adapted from [25]

• Real world project
• Experience applying Scrum
 AT1: Short quizzes about Scrum AT2: Group project




TABLE IV.
MEDIANS PER ITEM OF THE SURVEY
Applying Scrum with Taiga
Item T1* T2**
 No.
. (p)
.779
.487
.888 .280
.081
.141 .716 .294
. (p)
.845 .716
.779
.506 .888
.888
.648 .509
. (p)
.888 .416
.291
.944 --

1 Taiga allows me to understand the concept 4.0 4.0 ‘Product Backlog'
2 It allows me to communicate with other team 3.0 3.0 members
3 It eases the learning of Scrum 4.0 3.5
4 It eases the tracking of users’ stories and tasks 5.0 4.0
It facilitates a clear understanding of the daily 5.0 3.5

work that each team member has to do.
6 It eases the sprint planning 5.0 4.0
7 It eases the monitoring of sprint’s tasks 4.0 4.0
8 It is clear how to manage a sprint backlog 4.0 3.0
Usability of Taiga
No. Item T1* T2**
1 The tool is easy to use 4.0 3.5

TABLE III. CRONBACH’S ALFA VALUES
7 It is appropriate for beginners. 4.0 3.0
8 I think most people can quickly learn to use 4.0 3.0
the tool.
Adaptability to changes
No. Item T1* T2**
It allows me to quickly find all the 3.0 3.0 commands and buttons to create & assign
tasks.
The functionalities are integrated (e.g. It is 4.0 4.0
3 possible to add tasks right after creating a user story).
5
6
The tool can be learned in a short time. 4.0 4.0 It is easy to remember the location of the 4.0 3.5 menus, panels and buttons
I felt sure of what I was doing while using 4.0 3.5 the tool
 Instrument section
1. Application of Scrum using the Taiga tool
2. Usability of Taiga
3. Students’ adaptabilty to changes
Cronbach’s Alpha .892
.890
Changes are positive 4.0 4.0 When someone suggests to change
something that I have done, I accept it as it 4.0 4.0 can be beneficial
I feel comfortable exploring new 4.0 4.0 knowledge fields
I feel comfortable changing my routine 4.0 4.0 I enjoy learning new things 5.0 5.0

 

78-1-5090-5467-1/17/$31.00 ©2017 IEEE
* N = 17; ** N = 21
25-28 April 2017, Athens, Greece

TABLE V. TEST OF EQUALITY OF DISTRIBUTIONS OF SCORES AT THE QUIZ

TABLE VI.
Team 1 Team2 Team3 Team4 Team5
LEVEL OF COMPLIANCE OF THE SOFTWARE
 Customer Teacher 1
2 2 3 3 3 4 2 2 4 3
Teacher 2
3 4 3 2 3
Teacher 3
2 3 4 2 4
   Sum of right Sum of right Sum of right answers (T0)* answers (T1)** answers (T2)*
526 567 656 677 776 266 656 766 776 666 677 675 746 637 576 366 676 77 77 57 67
* N = 21; ** N = 17; p = 0.381

