Learning and Teaching Software Process Models Some Lessons Learned

Abstract—Software process models are fairly abstract tools for organizing large, complex software development projects. Since particularly undergraduate students commonly do not have any experience in being part of such a project, their understanding of the benefits and shortcomings of particular process models is very limited. Even more, frequently they are not aware of the need to follow a particular process model since their previous one-person software assignments were too small for requiring any such model at all.
In this paper, we share some experiences on how we tried to make the role and details of software process models more tangible for students. To that end, we chose two didactic approaches, namely problem-based-learning and project work. For the latter, we conducted fairly complex software development projects in teams of 4 to 6 students in their final year. Most of these projects were run in parallel teams, using different software process models to accomplish the same task. Our experience shows that this setting allows students to get a much better understanding of the characteristics of process models, but also indicate that students tend to get acquainted to traditional plan-driven process models more easily compared to agile models such as SCRUM or Extreme Programming.
As an instance of problem-based learning, students needed to develop a board game that addresses some of the specifics of a particular process model, namely the V-Model.

Keywords: Software engineering didactics; Learning arrangements for software engineering; Software process models, Unified Process, V-Model, SCRUM, Extreme Programming; Software engineering tools

I. INTRODUCTION
Developing software is a complex task. Traditionally, students initially focus on technical difficulties in terms of getting used to programming using a particular programming language like Java, C, or C++. These programming assignments, however, are not really realistic since they are precisely specified and supposed to be solved in a one-person effort. In contrast, real software projects are a multi-person effort, requiring a lot of coordination among stakeholders as well as among team members. Furthermore, requirements tend to be unclear for quite a
while, in particular if a real external customer with a different cultural background is involved.
Under these circumstances, an ad-hoc approach is inadequate for delivering a successful project. Over the years, several software process models have been proposed in order to provide more or less strict guidelines for organizing joint work on a project in a disciplined fashion. Traditionally, plan-driven methods such as, e.g., the waterfall model [1], the German VModel [2] or the Unified Process (UP) [3] can be used in large projects if requirements are sufficiently clear and stable, thus allowing thorough planning already at an early stage of the project. In recent years, however, it became obvious that these process models are not suitable for quite a few projects since their requirements are far from being clear at the outset, with a high change rate during the project. In order to embrace change, agile process models such as, e.g., Extreme Programming (XP) [4] or Scrum [5][6] have been proposed during the last decade. Their key characteristics are short iteration cycles instead of time-consuming big releases and intensive customer involvement. Furthermore, requirements are clarified continuously through personal communication rather than writing elaborate requirements specifications early in the project.
Due to the students’ lack of experience with large projects, teaching the specifics of process models is hard: students only have a limited understanding why process models are a prerequisite for that type of projects, let alone get a grip on the details of particular process models. The latter is due to the fact that at first sight traditional plan-driven models seem to be little more than common sense, while agile methods tend to appear chaotic rather than disciplined.
Thus, a traditional teaching and learning arrangement in which an instructor lectures on the characteristics of various process models is insufficient as single didactic approach.
A promising approach for providing a better understanding of abstract issues like process models is problem-based learning [7]. In particular, one of the authors tried to improve students’ understanding of process models by having students develop a V-Model board game.
As a second approach, we supplement the classical lecture style of teaching with a hands-on component, having our students work on a relatively complex software development project. A specific aspect of these projects lies in the fact that several teams work in parallel on basically the same assignment, but are requested to follow different process models. Thus, each team not only gains a better understanding, but also acquires competencies in actually using a process model.
The two didactic approaches have so far been used separately at two universities, but seem to supplement each other well.
In the next section, we discuss some details on the V-Model board game assignment and the feedback we gained.
This will be followed by details on the contents and imposed restrictions on the software development projects which we have run in the last two years. After setting the scene, we present some of the experiences we gained from running this type of project.
Finally, we draw some conclusions on the efficacy of our approaches and present an outlook on future activities.

II. PROBLEM-BASED LEARNING OF SOFTWARE PROCESS MODELS
A. A Board Game for Understanding the V-Model
Problem-based learning (PBL) as a non-traditional teaching method is used to improve students’ learning of a software engineering process model. The V-Model was selected as an example for a course unit.
There is no unique and commonly accepted definition and description of PBL. It is used to refer to numerous contextualized approaches to instruction that fasten learning and teaching in real problems. The focus on concrete problems as initiating the learning process is vital in most definitions. For example, Barrows and Tamblyn [7] define PBL as “learning that results from the process of working toward the understanding or resolution of a problem”.
According to Schmidt [8], problem-based learning consists of seven steps:
1. Clarify and agree on terms and concepts that are unclear.
2. Define the problem and review terms which need more depth or explanation.
3. Analyze, brainstorm, and create potential hypotheses.
4. Discuss, evaluate, and organize possible explanations into potential hypotheses.
5. Generate and prioritize learning objectives, divide research workload.
6. Study research objectives individually.
7. Report back gained information during the next tutorial session, create an explanation, and synthesize new information in relation to the problem.
PBL is used successfully in software engineering education at the Regensburg University of Applied Sciences. The instructor structures the learning goals according to Bloom's taxonomy [9][10] and creates a case study as part of the course preparation. The used PBL case study is shown in Figure 1. The case study centers around a problem situation of a virtual software company called Minocroft. Students are encouraged to develop a V-Model board game based on the case study.

The instructor explains the structure of the PBL methodology to the students. The students should be aware of the PBL steps and follow them consciously. In order to ensure this, one student, the so-called PBL clock manager, is responsible for supervising the proper execution of the seven PBL steps. In figure 2 the students collected the learning content in the form of a V-Model 97 [2] board game (Step 7 of PBL).
The board game consists of an adjustment of process stages, various event cards with questions regarding real intervention during software development, and knowledge-oriented cards with questions that target methods and techniques of software engineering.
The instructor accompanies the students’ learning process as a PBL moderator. In addition, he actively supports students through interventions, provides literature references and conversations on the strategy, and helps in the visualization of intermediate results. The use of PBL approach requires the provision of seminar rooms for group work and suitable literature in the libraries of universities.
A further advantage of the used PBL based approach is that students learn the software engineering process before the real students’ project starts. The students upstart out in a game-oriented manner to understand the complexity of a software engineering process. V-Model 97 is used as a representative example.
The board game comprises the following software engineering process phases of V-Model 97 which also can be found in other software engineering process models, like Unified Process or SCUM:
 Requirements engineering
 Analysis
 Design
 Implementation
 Module test
 Integration test
 System test
The board game can be adopted and extended to other process models. For instance, event cards with questions regarding SCRUM specific issues could be a future extension when using this learning arrangement.

B. The Learning Arrangement in Retrospective
A survey among instructors and students provided several insights.
It could be observed that learners are encouraged in the used self-directed PBL approach because they can decide on their learning issues independently. Students spent more time for preparing their issues with literature from university library. The instructor gives guidance and acts only as companion and consultant. The introduction and motivation for self-directed learning, however, is essential in the beginning of the course.
Quality assurance of the learning arrangement is accomplished by interventions of the instructor. The instructor gives hints to literature and the methodology. The learning arrangement adapts itself to the individual experience. Each student can contribute to the learning process, e.g. with his own internship experience.
Following the seven steps of PBL, the stages of PBL allow different ways of learning. Also action-orientation is provided by the PBL approach. Every PBL group develops an individual learning culture. Learning in multiple contexts is possible.
The described PBL learning with a V-Model 97 board game phase is followed by a laboratory software project. The students apply the previously learned software process model. Therefore PBL is a useful technique to support learning and further application of software engineering process models.
The Bologna agreement of the European Universities implies a shift from teaching to learning. It has been recognized that young academics need a lot of skills for creative engineering work. The PBL model of learning supports the development of the following skills among software engineering students:
 Responsibilities assumed in the group,
 Constructive criticism,
 Organization and manipulation of non-structured information,
 Critical thinking, initiative and search for information,
 Oral communication and written skills.
In PBL, we are not only trying to develop knowledge which is important in every learning process. In addition, we attempt to develop professional skills that will help students during their learning process and their professional life.

III. LEARNING THE UNIFIED PROCESS AND AGILE DEVELOPMENT IN A SOFTWARE PROJECT
Projects are a didactic approach that allows students to go beyond a mere understanding of abstract issues. In addition to that, they acquire competencies in applying their knowledge to a real problem setting. For that reason, projects seem to be a promising approach to get deeper insights into the specifics of software process models.

A. Our Approach
In order to simulate a real software project, students in our module at Coburg University of Applied Sciences were divided into teams of 4 to 6 individuals. Each team was in charge of realizing a software product according to a specific process model. In our first year, one team implemented an editor for business process models using SCRUM as process model. Two teams developed an editor for petri nets but according to different process models, namely SCRUM and Unified Process.
In our second year, two teams were assigned to creating a web portal to collect research project data und publications using SCRUM resp. XP. For this task an on-site customer defined the requirements.
To increase motivation we also allow students to propose own ideas for projects. A software platform for freelancers is one example of such a proposal that we realized in our second year.

B. Teaching Goals and Imposed Constraints
After participating in the project the students should
 obtain hands-on experience on how to realize and manage larger software projects,
 gain a deeper understanding of all software development phases and the various process models,
 improve their ability to work in a team while developing software.
To achieve these goals and to get broader knowledge about the differences between process models, some general restrictions were imposed on deliverables and process rules.
First, each team had to fill predefined roles, namely project manager, systems analyst, software architect, configuration and build manager, programmer, test manager [11]. Each team member has to be involved in coding.
Secondly, some constraints were imposed concerning the treatment of requirements. Every team was required to write a requirements specification which included the specification of use cases, irrespective of which particular process model the team was using. The teams were allowed to differ, however, in the point in time when this requirements document was written. Also, the degree of completeness was depending on the specific process model. In agile process models, requirements documents are enhanced during each iteration, starting from a fairly incomplete first version. The requirements specification establishes the basis for an early quality gate which should provide feedback to the team as to whether they were doing well or not. To that end, a formal review [12][13] of the requirements documents was conducted for each team.
Also, a software architecture document was requested as an additional deliverable.
Furthermore, systematic test case deduction and implementation of regression tests was requested from all teams. A minimum branch coverage [14][15] of 75 percent was required for the final system test execution.
Tools from the following categories were used to enable efficient software development: project management (MS Project [16] for plan-driven processes, Agilo [17] or Pivotal Tracker [18] for agile development), modeling (Innovator [19]), build (Apache AntTM [20]) and configuration management (Subversion [21] or Git [22]), test execution (JUnit [23]) and test coverage (Cobertura [24]) .

C. Module Details
As a precondition for such a software project module all participants need to be familiar with software engineering fundamentals of all lifecycle phases. These fundamentals are covered in a mandatory course one year before the project. This course also addresses the basics of various process models in a “traditional” teaching fashion. Nevertheless, beyond these software engineering principles teams have to get acquainted with a variety of advanced topics (e.g. project and iteration planning, effort estimation, comprehensive software architecture definition, formal reviews) through self-directed learning. Instructors act as coaches who help and guide the teams if necessary, e.g. by providing pointers to relevant literature.
The project module is assigned 6 credit points (180 hours effort) and requires a weekly student presence of about half a day. Student grading involves several components: an individual grade, a team grade for the final product delivery and additional documents (requirements specification, architecture document), and a grade for the final presentation of the project’s results.

D. Projects as a Learning Style for Software Process Models
In our basic software engineering course, students acquire theoretical knowledge on software process models, but have no opportunity to apply it. Since projects provide them with such an opportunity, they are a very good didactic strategy to learn and teach software process models.
Project work is an integral and integrative learning style, focused on student-centered and group learning. The educational goal of a project is primarily to enable students to transfer their theoretical knowledge, e.g. on software process models, to a real problem setting, thus acquiring competence in a particular area [25]. Obtaining additional factual knowledge is only a side effect. Students are supposed to learn to act problem-oriented. Project work enables students to benefit from what they learned and cope with everyday challenges.
Project work is a self-directed learning process. Within the team the students need to organize the complete process in a self-directed fashion. The entire team has to plan the process and is jointly responsible for all results. The project team has to develop a project plan with mile stones and needs to keep a deadline. Furthermore, the project team autonomously defines project aims, identifies and puts work steps in a reasonable sequence, carries out these activities, and controls the result.
Time management is also part of project work. Students are responsible for their own schedule.
Project work challenges students in various ways. Each of them has to find her professional role within the team: one of them needs to lead the team as project manager while others concentrate on software architecture or requirements analysis. Each role requires and trains different competencies. Furthermore, project work allows each student to check if the chosen role is appropriate for her.
Due to the need to interact, students train and improve their social and personal skills in addition to their professional competencies. Project work improves their ability to co-operate and forces them to think for themselves. They must manage themselves individually and as a team member. They have to learn to work as a team, co-operate within the team, listen to others, and speak clearly when they express own ideas. They have to discuss alternative solutions for whatever problem and then decide which way to go. Each decision must be supported by all team members: none of them can enforce an idea but rather needs to convince the other team members. In most cases, critique from peers is easier to accept for students than critical feedback from an instructor. Thus, project work develops self-access competence [26]. Among other aspects, self-access competence includes e.g. self-determination, self-responsibility, and self-reliance.
To be successful in projects students need to do much more than remember information. They need to use higher-order thinking skills. Higher-order thinking is characterized in learning taxonomies such as Bloom's [9]. The easiest category is to remember facts. This is the basis for understanding information. The third category focuses on the application of learned information. Higher-order thinking at the fourth level requires complex skills such as problem solving, critical thinking, and creation of new knowledge. Project work is a didactic strategy which teaches higher-order thinking.
In consequence, project work affects the whole learning person. Learning seems to be sustainable. There are indications [27] that we learn
10 % of things we read,
20 % of things we hear,
30 % of things we see,
50 % of things we hear and see,
70 % of things we explain to others, 90 % of things we do.
In fact, the more senses we use the more effective we learn. Already Comenius calls this didactic strategy "learning by doing" [28] and values it as one of his learning principles.
Project work emphasizes learning instead of teaching. The role of the instructor changes from transferring knowledge to facilitating to learn. The instructor is no longer the center of interest and loses his dominance in terms of planning and organization. . Rather, the instructor turns into a coach and consultant [29] who needs to rely on students to apply what they learned previously, even without getting clear instructions. Consequently, projects require multiple competences also from the instructor: he has to stay on top of things and be aware of when he is needed by the students. The instructor has to pay attention to a multitude of aspects: He has to be familiar with all students including their individual competencies and personalities, he must be aware of group dynamics in the project teams, and he has to observe the progress of the students and their projects. Thus he monitors, analyzes, supports, and evaluates numerous parallel individual learning processes simultaneously.
In order to accomplish this, the instructor requires soft skills in addition to pure knowledge. In particular, the instructor needs methodological competence such as communication skills or work techniques because students take him as a role model. Also, a different attitude is required with respect to students: the instructor needs to accept them as close-to-peers rather than view them as some advanced type of pupil.
All in all, instructors of project work have to be able and willing to challenge their role. They must have confidence in their ability to teach and in the learning achievements of their students. Furthermore, instructors must be open enough to accept unusual solutions which differ from their original expectations.

E. Experiences
1) Customizing is complex, in particular in agile process models
When confronted with a real project, students quickly realize that textbook knowledge alone is not sufficient for a successful implementation of a process model, simply because the situations they encounter are different from the ones described in textbooks. This is particularly true in agile process models.
Agile methods assume that the project team works full time on the project. Since the students in our projects do have further obligations, e.g. additional courses or their bachelor thesis, this assumption does not hold. To make things worse, individual schedules differ significantly among teammates, leading to a considerable amount of offline work. Thus, communication within the project cannot be accomplished exclusively with short daily meetings, such as daily scrums. Students tend to use Skype as a medium for communication and synchronize themselves two or three times per week.
Agile process models also require easy access to customers for clarifying requirements whenever the need arises. This is accomplished through an on-site customer [4] in XP or the product owner [5] in Scrum. In our project settings, access to customers turned out to be difficult. For project assignments without a real customer, the instructors tried to fill this role. In projects with a real customer, a one hour meeting was scheduled once a week. In both cases, offline questions of the development team had to be answered by electronic mail due to limited physical availability of customer representatives.
The so-called Scrum master [5] is the third essential role in Scrum in addition to product owner and development team. The Scrum master is intended to act as an interface of the development team towards product owner and line management. In particular, the Scrum master is responsible to ensure that Scrum’s rules and principles are followed properly. A prerequisite for being a Scrum master is extensive experience with Scrum. Since all of the students were lacking this type of experience, the Scrum teams had to cope without a proper Scrum master. The project manager had to act as a substitute for the Scrum master.
In contrast to agile process models, the Unified Process (UP) expects extensive documentation in a variety of documents. Students following UP tend to assume that all of these documents are required in every project. Even after being informed that it is perfectly legal to omit some documents, it turned out to be pretty difficult for students to decide which document is valuable enough to be written in a particular project.

2) Use cases are not as easy as they seem to be
In contrast to UP which views use cases as a core constituent of the process, agile methods start with an even more abstract approach to requirements. Scrum commonly uses so-called user stories [6], while XP embarks on a similar concept, namely so-called story cards [4]. Essentially, requirements are expressed as one-line statements from a user perspective. Both process models argue that stories need to be detailed when they are addressed in an iteration, but leave it to the development team to decide how exactly this will be accomplished. In order to alleviate this, we imposed the constraint to embark on use cases for making high-level requirements more concrete. In employing use cases for this purpose, we are in line with common practice [30] to fill this void in agile process models.
Although use cases had been exercised extensively in previous courses, students had considerable difficulties in defining and specifying use cases properly. They had a fatal tendency towards very fine-grained use cases and modeling control flow among use cases through stereotyped associations («extend» / «include») in use case diagrams. In addition, scenarios within use cases often turned out to be written in a fairly realization-specific manner, expressing particular design options (“...push the select button on the left of the entry to be chosen...”) rather than being focused on requirements.
In order to establish an early quality gate, the requirements document including all the use cases is formally reviewed by the project team and one of the instructors. In hindsight, students view this formal review as very helpful even if some of the comments in the review initially seemed to be close to nitpicking. Furthermore, they accept a high-quality requirements specification as an essential prerequisite for a project to be successful.

3) Planning is not easy, either
Even though agile methods are intended to be responsive to changes, planning is also an issue for these approaches. A core part of XP for planning is the so-called planning game [4], while Scrum mostly relies on so-called story points [6] for effort estimation.
Prioritization of requirements worked fairly well in our projects, while effort estimation did not. Story points provide only a relative, rather than an absolute estimate of the effort that is required for realizing a particular story. Lacking a proper baseline, effort estimation did not work well. Instead, we recommended use case points [31] as an alternative, given the fact that the teams had to write use cases anyway. It turned out that use case points had a tendency to overestimate the effort for individual use cases, but captured the overall effort fairly well. In hindsight, real and estimated effort differed by only 10 percent in some teams.
Effort estimation and planning was done primarily in the developer team. The on-site customer participated only in assigning priorities to stories, but there was no proper planning game.

4) Being agile is difficult...
Simple design is one of the principles of agile process models, particularly in XP [4]. As a consequence, the system has to be restructured in later iterations when additional requirements need to be considered. Our students, however, did not embark too easily on agile thinking. Instead, they spent quite some time on getting the system architecture right early in the project, even though they did not have a clear picture of all the requirements yet. In their mind, refactoring would amount to throw away valuable work and start over from scratch. Having such a mindset, these teams would have been better off following a plan-based process.

5) A wrong view of testing activities
Nearly all teams underestimate especially the testing effort. Due to the required branch coverage of 75 percent and the usage of test coverage tools teams clearly see whether test cases are still missing or not. In addition, teams which were developing test implementations according to XP’s Test Driven Development (TDD) approach [32] typically achieved higher test coverage with less required functionality, whereas teams without TDD approach delivered more functionality based on a worse test coverage. Furthermore, TDD teams were only productive if the architecture and interfaces were defined precisely in advance. Otherwise a time consuming refactoring of test case implementations was necessary, which increased the test development effort and lowered motivation.
All in all, all teams delivered their product with the required branch coverage in spite of the described difficulties. Moreover, at the end of the project students have a much better understanding about the importance and pitfalls of testing activities within the software engineering process.

6) Sometimes performing team roles is difficult
Due to the lack of experience with individual roles and a wrong self-assessment of their strengths and weaknesses, a reassignment of roles after project start became necessary in some teams. The essential team collaboration, however, works very well, especially also in situations, in which teams must solve team conflicts constructively.

7) Motivation is high
Two main aspects in project work support the motivation of students. First of all, they have a vital influence on the project as they organize their work process autonomously. Secondly, project work increases self-confidence since the instructor trusts the students to get good results without telling them exactly what to do next.
These general phenomena could also be observed in our projects: students were very interested in the functionality and application domain of their software product. In addition, the project setting nurtured competition because different teams had to realize a software product with the same functionality. None of the teams wanted to fall behind others in terms of functionality, quality, and time schedule. Thus, some teams delivered more functionality than requested. For instance, the teams which realized the Petri net environments not only implemented editing facilities, but also decided to add simulation capabilities.
All teams spent considerable effort in order to achieve a successful project finish. Some teams worked significantly harder than would be expected for a course module of 6 credit points.

8) Evaluation of individual contributions
Project work also causes one principal difficulty, namely the evaluation of individual contributions to the result of a team effort. Matters are complicated further by the fact that teams work on different assignments. There is no easy way of comparing results across teams. Even if teams work on the same assignment they use different software process models. The teams only get a framework, but each team organizes and manages its work process. Since regulations require individual grading, we tried to cope with these difficulties by means of two components.
First of all, we requested a project diary from each team which contained an account of how much time team members spent on which particular task. This project diary finally had to be signed by each team member.
Secondly, each team presented its result at the end of the project. In this final presentation, each team member needed to explain (some of) her individual contributions and expose them to the critique of peers and instructors. This worked pretty well since weaker contributions quickly became obvious in the discussion.
Alternatively, it would have been possible to have individual oral examinations at the end of a project. In this one-to-one meeting, each student has to explain her work in the project. Such a setting allows an instructor to judge individual contributions easily. This approach, however, generates higher effort than team presentations without leading to significantly deeper insights in our particular setting.

IV. SUMMARY AND FUTURE WORK
Software engineering encompasses plenty of abstract concepts that are hard to grasp for a student. Software process models are just one example of such an abstract matter. Traditional teaching methods can convey only lower-level knowledge in learning taxonomies such as Bloom’s [9]. In order to support higher-order thinking skills, additional and/or alternative approaches to learning are required.
We gained some experience with problem-based learning, in particular the assignment to develop a board game to highlight the specifics of the V-Model and a project-based approach for teaching and learning software process models.
Generally, students appreciated these approaches since they are in a much more active role within the learning process. The role of the supervisors changes from instructors to moderators or coaches. Thus, students are responsible for their own learning processes to a much larger extent than in a traditional setting.
Problem-based learning can be used in situations when resources, in particular time, are limited. Projects are fairly timeconsuming since they reflect reality as closely as possible in a university context. While problem-based learning supports obtaining a deeper understanding of abstract issues, it falls short in terms of acquiring competencies in applying the respective issues. The latter seems to be possible only through project work.
The feedback of participants is encouraging. Although they complained about considerable effort they had to spent, in particular in projects, they conceded that they gained extremely many insights. When asked if they would participate in the course again, the majority of students would do so in spite of the required effort. Even when students had to admit that their solution was not optimal, they now knew how to do better in
their next project – in particular, which mistakes should not be repeated.
Problem-based learning and project work are not only a challenge for students, but also for instructors. Both didactic approaches require complex competencies also from the instructors and their willingness to learn, too.
So far, the two approaches have been used in their own right. As a next step, we would like to use the two approaches jointly in order to get a better understanding how they can supplement each other. In particular, the basic software engineering course that lays the ground for project work could be enriched with elements of problem-based learning. Thus, a good understanding of process models could be achieved already before the project. This would be in line with one of the recommendations of Stapel et al. [33].
Also, running the project as a block course rather might be an option for future repetitions of the project module [33], thus fulfilling the assumption of fulltime work on the project more closely.