Scrum Higher Education – The Scrum Master Supports as Solution-focused Coach

Abstract   The article proposes to determine, discuss and qualify how the Framework Scrum Higher Education  based on the original Framework Scrum Version 2017  supports teachers and students to recognize the difficulties and chal lenges related to the intended learning outcome and the miss ing motivation of students  learning process. The study aims to answer several research questions, e.g. what is the effect of a valuebased framework and the intervention by a Scrum Master on students  agile and critical performance in team work? The team performance was diagnosed by applying a set of tools to measure the capacity for teamwork. The evaluation confirms that agile and collaborative adaption of Scrum for Higher Education improves the selflearning process, self motivation and selfemotion for the learner. Especially the event SprintRetrospective with the tailormade framework for the Definition of Flow plays a key role and the Scrum Master gets a chance for solutionfocused coaching in a convenient phase of reflection. The paper shows empirical results of a quantitative survey, which analyses quality criteria of teamwork during the sprints of the Scrum Framework. As an agile method of learning, students figured out their own learning and team working obstacles by using the solution focused coaching.

Keywords - Scrum Higher Education, Solutionfocused Coaching, Teamwork TCI, Agile Learning

I. INTRODUCTION
The development of Scrum Higher Education (Scrum-HE) should disseminate principles that do not only guarantee agile teaching for software engineering but also for engineers in other technical domains. Therefore, the original Framework Scrum Version 2017 [1] was adapted and specified by [2] as an agile method to further the learning-rocess. It includes the classic Scrum events of Sprint-the container for all other events-with Sprint-Planning, Daily Scrum, Sprint-Review and Sprint-Retrospective.

The self-reflecting element of the Sprint-Retrospective (Retro) is mainly specified [2] in the Definition of Flow. In order to find the right idea of what (self-) reflexivity means for the team, we use solution-oriented coaching through the agile commitment of the Scrum Master as Solution-focused Coach (SFC). Therefore, the Quick Check of Flow will foster a change in the next Sprint for both students and the team as a whole, if there is a need of learning strategy or more motivation and emotion. This creates a starting point for continuous improvement of learning, how to work as a team and for developing the skills of self-determination and lifelong learning.


II. BACKGROUND

A. Description and Impact Specification of Scrum-HE

The objective of the presented agile concept of Scrum HE is to shortly describe the most important events, artifacts and roles. Fig. 1 illustrates all elements of ScrumHE in our applied process of learning in accordance with the main impacts of [37]. We start explaining the Figure 1 in the blue box on the left side, which is here the main part of the valuable framework for learning and teamwork in higher education. Students with the roles of Vice Scrum Master, Vice Product Owner and the Team as well form the Scrum Team. In the following, the two terms are used interchangeably.

First, the students are given the task of finding the five most important values as described in [1]: Commitment, focus, respect, openness and courage. Sensibilized with a value management by using 140 value cards, given by [8], they may seize this as a first opportunity for reflecting their own values. The second step is to bring team members closer to each other. They discuss their values with their team members, harmonize the differences in values and establish their common five Scrum Team values. Therefore, we use this so-called Five-Finger-Feedback method [9] as a reflexion-tool, where each finger of one hand represents a specific value in the teams’ value system. By creating familiar team values, students are committed to learning in the community and openly share their insights with the team. The motivation and emotion experienced by each other contribute to the cohesion and influence both the student's own learning progress and that of the team. At the end of the learning process these values are reflected once again, when the SFC asks the student or the team: “Have you lived within your possibilities during your learning process? What are you doing in order to achieve the best possible outcome”.

The next preconditions to start the didactical approach for higher education are the following and reflect the Plan-Do-Check-Act (PDCA) or rather the Plan-Do-Check-Learn (PDCL) cycle as the real holistic process of learning like the conceptions of [1 –​7]:

The Curriculum Including Competencies with Intended Learning Outcomes describes discussed goals with and for External Stakeholders. These goals of the learning process are written down as User Stories and listed as learning modules collected in the so-called Product Backlog. This documentation can intend scenario-, problem- and project- or research-based tasks. The intended learning outcome requires appropriate instructions and helpful delivery advices, which are summarized as Definitions of Ready. A teacher or an external professional in the role of the Product Owne r, who demands a quality standardized (learning-) product in an allowed time duration, formulates them. They are also tested for feasibility.

That is the reason why the Product Backlog Items portion the learning units in schedulable sizes, preparing them for the Sprint. In Higher Education, the Sprint could span a week or even longer from one lesson to another. It depends on the decision of the Product Owner and the content of the Product Backlog, which is specified by the Definition of Done.

The student group, as Scrum Team, schedules and determines the right scope of activities with the support of the appointed Vice-Scrum Master. This meeting is called Sprint Planning. The work to be done requires team members who have the knowledge, skills and competences for creative task solving and a high degree of personal responsibility for the quality of the results. This phase reflects the Plan.

The Vice-Scrum Master maintains the User Stories and Activities by using a collaborative online-platform with professional Scrum-Tools, e.g. Backlog, Sprint Board, Scrum Board and customized user administration with mobile access. That is the reason why in Scrum-HE the Daily Scrum can take place without physical presence of the Scrum Team and offers high transparency, as well as chances for inspection and adaptation. This phase reflects the Do.

The Sprint Review takes place at a previously chosen sprint deadline at which the team deals with current sprint goals. During the presentation of their work, the Product Owner evaluates the Definition of Done and as well the acceptance criteria, if the Scrum Team have been achieved them. This phase reflects the Check.

The Retro is essentially the most important part and follows directly after the Sprint Review. The goals are to inspect, understand and adapt the interactions among learning aptitudes, strategies and knowledge in cognitive performance. The opportunity requires the Scrum Team and the individual person to create a plan for improving themselves and the collaboration with an increased teamwork. By answering the questions for the Quick Check of Flow, which are linked to questionnaire of the Team Climate Inventory Items, the students develop a mind-set for agility needs and agile methods of teamwork and joint learning. Therefore, the definition of agility should be the ability to continuously adapt to its complex, future- and solution-focused needs. This phase reflects the Learn.

The concept should be encouraged by a SFC who operates in a sustainable manner. It requires lecturers or Master students with basic knowledge and mutual understanding for psychological needs in motivation, development and wellness in self-determination theory [10], to be able to develop better self-organized and creative team-solutions and to understand the required psychological needs for students´ action.


B. Solution-focused Coaching

The Scrum Master acts as a serving counselor and as SFC, who guides students identifying and clarifying their needs. “Problem talk creates problems; solution talk creates solutions” [11]. With this sentence, S. de Shazer initiates his special solution-focused brief therapy founded in 1985, which is nowadays used by school counselors. Through specific questioning techniques, empathy, emotional intelligence and use of encouragement, what students are promoted in their strength. The SFC guides them in finding solutions and creating expectations of positive changes for their own process of learning. The methodological approach helps students identify their capabilities, use their resources efficiently and foster self-awareness. Here it is important that the SFC oneself can exercise both mindfulness and self-regulation. The Scrum Master is the key actor who shapes the project and therefore the learning environment and whose main task includes motivating students to learn by using autonomy-supportive strategies instead of final controlling behaviors. In order for the Scrum Team to achieve their joint learning goals Sprint by Sprint, it requires a guide like a SFC, who is passionate about the impact of agile teaching and embodies agility. This person is characterized as someone with strong facilitation skills and a collaborative, proactive and structured working style. His or her task is to make the Retro a safe place where everyone can talk about risky things. In this situation, the Scrum Master can start to build trust by steering the conversation toward feel-good items. Furthermore, he or she needs strong communication and visualization skills. To master strong moderation with high ability to work in a team, conflict handling and coaching skills in order to identify and overcome or mitigate impediments is the daily of life. Retros help teams examine what went right and what went wrong. The Team is adept to communicate in high bandwidth without undue inference. It enables invaluable reflection processes and the development of individually customized strategies. This can also trigger important learning processes, e.g. with regard to teamwork and change management, building collaborative relationships and talking about possible alternate futures. Giving up complaining has the effect of arousing the expectation that change management is possible [12, 13].

C. Factors of team-oriented Learning

As shown above, the quality of team performance is strongly related to the Scrum Master’s actions. Now that the Scrum Team is aware about its performance, it is time for the discussion about the meta-cognitive learning strategies and the reflection of the teamwork using the Team Climate Inventory. The basis reference published by Anderson and West as Team Climate Inventory (TCI) can be used to evaluate interventions in respect to their effects on Team Climate [14]. The German construction [15] is a cultural and linguistic adaptation of the British original and involves the four-factors: vision, participative safety, task orientation and support for innovation. C. H. Antoni [16] reviewed the German version. In his opinion it can be considered as a „well documented, reliable and comparatively valid instrument“ [16].

The procedure of administrating the scale of team members was as follows: Fourteen teams agreed to participate, giving a total sample size of 78 students. In each of these 14 different groups ranged between four and seven members. A typical team consists of an assistant Scrum Master, an assistant Product Owner and the learning Scrum Team members.

Therefore, the TCI was adapted finding valuable evaluation results by intervention of a Scrum Master as a SFC. This is why in scientific research the character of Team Climate is often distinguished among several aspects. N. R. Anderson and M. A. West [14] differentiate between four factors. Considering three factors vision, participative safety and task orientation, it is possible to get a better understanding about the quality of teamwork. The last factor namely innovation is negligible, because the students’ tasks are given contextualized, i.e. characterized by existing and realistic life and not by requirements of future products or deliverables. In our paper, we only illustrate the two most important factors Vision and Task Orientation of seven factor details in total.

Table I shows the results in the Vision factor, which is defined as an idea of a valued outcome representing a higher goal and involve clarity (easy to understand), value of team objectives (valued outcome, visible to individuals in the group), sharedness (extension of the Vision) and attainability (achievable widespread acceptance).

The research of [15] added the so-called output-orientation as a new factor to the German version. This factor design seems very suitable for solution-focused approaches and the definition includes the following characters:

    High standards characterized by the effort to score high in performance and quality in the common objectives achievement

    Reflection continuously executed and with high mindfulness as an attribute that can be actively cultivated.

    Synergy and constructive discussions about contentious issues.

Despite uncertainty, ambiguity and dissent in factual and technical questions, the team members can nevertheless find out their individual competencies. Thereby greater openness to their joint expert knowledge and mindful reflection can be self-cultivated. People can thus become more mindful, more aware, and more autonomous as a sustainable step for the next Sprint. Table II demonstrates these development possibilities. However, it should be pointed out that these factor-components are the most important for the Retro. In conclusion, the Scrum Master as a SFC has a vital role in the Scrum Framework.


 SECTION III.
Evaluation of the Retrospective

To point up the Sprint-Retrospective as the phase of learning, a real situation of solving a challenge illustrates the performance, which is measured by evaluating of the TCI Items. Only a small change in the Scrum Master's behavior was necessary, so that all team members get the right impression of the team goals at the right time. This led to profound and far-reaching differences in the behavior of all persons involved, which resulted in more improvements as planned. Even the Scrum Master and the Product Owner participated in that close collaboration. Inversely, it seems that the bigger the goal or the desired change, the harder it will be to establish a cooperative relationship between all roles, and the more likely that the team will fail. The student’s action after PDCL represents the real learning phase. In particular, the recurring opportunities of Retro create a formal Framework requirement in a specific way as will be described in table II. This is also the highlight of the main objectives. It helps to sensitize participants to their reflection capacity, which is a necessary precondition to shape the learning process adapted to them.

Even through the team development stages, we can create an environment in which Scrum Teams perform at their peak. In this situation a structured agenda and the golden rules of the Retro along with the tool-based Quick Check of Flow [17, 18] support the students as well as the team to establish the need to adjust their behavior in the next Sprint and to enhance a continuous improvement process.

In table I and table II the total amount of points and the percentage of the increase of evaluation-points after a Retro session demonstrate the immense influence of the Scrum Master as the SFC. The factor details described by the evaluation points give an impression of distribution and frequency of valued aspects.

A. Factor Vision

First, the factor Vision highlights four subareas:
Groups with a common Vision are more motivated to develop new solution-oriented methods of working.

The clarity of the team objectives increased by 11.3% after Scrum Team interacted with the Scrum Master who moderates the Retro. This means that the objectives should fit the team in its current situation.

The value of team objectives appears to be 9.4% higher than before the Retro. Students in Scrum described the objectives as useful and appropriate, only 5.7% think, that these objectives are valuable to their own team.

The sharedness of 78 mentions concerns the agreement to other team members with 450 points before the Retro and only 20 points more after the invention of the Scrum Master. The next statement displays means that the group only has a commitment of 50% in average for own group objective interaction. This may be a question of trust and openness. The rates of increase for identification are lower as well, namely 5.4% and 4.1%. That could be due to a lack in clearness and may be a question of communication time.

In contrast to the other factor details, the attainability scored very high. In addition, it shows a significant increase of 11.8% concerning the team´s perspective after the Retro. The students realized that they are high performers with an average of nearly 8 points response range along with a change in student engagement by 9.2%.

This empirical study shows that students will be able to complete the target tasks in a calm and timely manner, if they receive right information in the right phase of Retro. They could use common experience better about improved progress than they expected in the new Sprint Planning procedure. However, the implementation of the Retro involves a shared responsibility, because all team members are committed to implementing the tasks in lean and agile best practice. The joint development of possible solutions is much more sustainable and effective. The small groups perform with high responsibility and their members influence each other, without the need for overtime.

B. Factor Output-orientation

Secondly, the factor output-orientation contains three subareas. This solution-focused coaching model allows us to provide relevant and specific support as well as advice for each team, at the time that they need it. R. Chatley [18] describes who to bring lean methods from industry to the classroom. However, solution-focused coaching plays a role for students in MINT-Courses as well.

Reaching for high standards plays a huge role, so that the team has to be convinced towards a continually monitoring. Nevertheless, that can also induce a certain physical pressure. You need wary to negative scenario this creates. The SFC is experienced and gives valuable advice for the next planning procedure. The score of this factor detail was improved 9.6%. This could be an indicator for the persuading power of the coach, but there is also a need to clear the criteria in the team to achieve the optimum as an entire team by realizing only 6.8%. The question as to what the optimum is has to be clarified for all members of the Scrum Team.

The reflection factor corresponds exactly to the most important phase of Scrum Framework event, the Retro. At first, we talk about the right selection of the technological knowledge, even the related and suitable, self-organized approach for the individual learning process. Secondly, a quite important point of developing student’s reflecting capacity is the instructional time of a Retro. That allows feedback and further mindful reflection for the team and for each related person, trustfully and contemporary, inspired by the Scrum Master as a SFC. Team members might perceive the continual control between them as being unpleasant. Students often cited the sentence of [1] that Scrum is lightweight and easy to understand but hard to master. They noticed that the development of discipline for themselves and the self-organized team is a big challenge as the improvement by respectively 5.1% and 2.8% shows. However, the survey evaluation per group confirms the conclusion, that teams who really explore their common values in the beginning of their teamwork and use the five-finger-feedback method as a guide for the Retro are more willing to critically appraise their potential weaknesses. This is shown by the high level increase of 11.4% after a moderated Retro.

The synergy factor with the question of helpful advice, encouragement and support in the community of colleagues has quite a high estimation of 558 points and improves to 634 points after the Retro, which is an increase of 13.6%. The evaluation of the effectiveness is even quite high with 546 points and increase 9.5% after the Scrum Master influence.


Conclusion and Perspective

An evaluation of the most important TCI factors and conclusion at the end summarizes the findings. We should put even more emphasis on solution-focused coaching as an instrument of integrated student advisory service, which uses the subject of study as a vehicle of a holistic self-development. Furthermore, it increases the success rate for software engineers. A long-term study will determine, discuss and qualify how the Framework Scrum-HE supports the lecturers in noticing the difficulties and challenges related to the intended learning outcome and the missing motivation in students’ learning procedures. The study proves that the use of Scrum-HE increases the team performance. This was diagnosed with the allocation of the TCI as certain inventory of measuring the better capacity for teamwork. The evaluation also confirms that Scrum-HE with the specific procedure of asking and answering questions in the Retro can be a sensitizer f self-learning competencies. In summary, it is worth noting that the workload for students does not seem to have increased, however functional results have improved. This is due to their shift in behavior towards the team during lectures. The responsibility of the Scrum roles causes more activity, e.g. discussing ideas and asking questions. Individual solution-focused coaching enables teams to adopt themselves appropriate tools and techniques for their specific context and to gain more nontechnical, social skills. A. Dehlii et al. [5] describe, “Incremental deliveries of ‘Done’ learning results ensure that a potentially good result towards the learning goals is always achievable.” and checks the learning process by using the Definition of Fun [6], which describes the “Definition of Happiness”. The future concept of Scrum Higher Education substantiates a Definition of Flow for the Retro. Verifying optimal challenges by a transformational SFC requires a concept of flow [17]. The workload for students does not seem to have increased. This is due to the fact that the behaviour of the individual changes towards during the Retro. They are very inquisitive, ask many questions and discuss solution ideas. A Scrum Master could use a catalogue of dedicated questions and devoted methods for Retrospectives [18, 19] in order to lead oneself, to lead students and to lead changes in Higher Education, so-called Transformative Leadership [20]. Some further guiding principles and useful approaches explore [20]: “It requires critical reflection on questions about for whom the system is working … calls for critical analysis of beliefs, values …”. As already mentioned, evidence through this study shows that excellent qualified SFC could be autonomy-supportive. The Retro employs the moderation-method “Two words …” [17] and the question sounds „What two words come to mind when you think of Scrum?” The answers were 50% division of work and less work, 30% better time management and timeliness, 20% teamwork with minimal effort and maximum of result. Helpful hints in each Retro provide orientation and cause time saving by effective team working. Moreover, this study gives further impacts for research developing self-learning, self-emotion, and self-motivation through Scrum Learning Process Coaching.

