 Agile Mindset Adoption in Student Team Projects

Abstract. Developing and maintaining complex software systems requires both technical expertise as well as soft skills such as teamwork and good communication abilities. These become even more important as the size and geographical distribution of teams grow. The adoption of Agile development methodologies further emphasizes interaction, collaboration and adaptability to change, all with the purpose of prioritizing working software. Organizations of higher education have acknowledged this by incorporating capstone or team projects as part of their curricula. Our exploratory study reports the experience of 47 teams of 3rd year Computer Science students, each tasked with developing a medium-sized software application as part of a Team Project course. We focus our work on the issues reported by student teams planning to take up Agile values and practices. We report the most important challenges faced during application development and present them from both the students’ and their mentors’ perspectives. We show that soft skills remain an important component of adopting an Agile mindset when teaching collaborative software engineering. We provide an open source replication package that allows repeating or extending our investigation.

Keywords: Software engineering education · Soft skills · Agile software development · Project · Empirical study

1 Introduction
Industry and society both expect students graduating from Universities to possess relevant professional skills that enable them to take up a productive role in a modern work environment. Generally, these ‘professional skills’ encompass hard skills and soft skills. The former denotes scientific and technical proficiency that enables graduates to develop complex software applications. The latter one denotes a complementary set of skills that enable professionals to work in a team environment where communication, collaboration and teamwork are essential, which we find to be the case when developing real-life applications [1]. The realization of the importance soft skills in modern software development, especially with the acknowledgement and adoption of Agile methodologies, have lead to the introduction of project-based coursework that provides students the opportunity to work in a collaborative environment that includes an important soft skills component.

The present paper follows our precursor study [13] that detailed the most important results of an exploratory study carried out in the context of implementing a project-based course. Its three most important characteristics were the development of real-life systems, feedback from mentors working in the local IT industry and several workshops focused on the adoption of soft skills and an Agile mindset. The course was available to third year Computer Science students at the Babes-Bolyai University. Students were expected to already posses a strong technical background with proficiency in several programming languages and associated popular frameworks and libraries. While most University courses were geared towards the development and evaluation of hard skills, the “Team Projects” course aimed to challenge students to overcome the challenges specific to working in a team and provide them with a solid, experience-driven foundation regarding the importance of soft skills and the advantages of Agile methods. Furthermore, the presence of mentors from the IT industry strengthens the collaboration between the University and local companies and helps provide students with a fresh perspective on their progress.

The main goal of the present work was to obtain an improved understanding of the students’ perception on the importance of soft skills and the way Agile methods could be leveraged in a more complex project. In addition to our previous work [13], we complemented our detailed examination regarding the accumulation of hard and soft skills with an evaluation of the importance and the impact made by adopting an Agile mindset. We used both student and mentor feedback together with the final project evaluation that was carried out by teaching staff experienced in the development of complex software systems. We published the questionnaires used for both students and mentors, together with all replies in order to enable replicating or extending our study [12].
Our current work further details our initial efforts [13] and follows the best practices outlined in [14]. We present some key aspects of software projects in education in Sect. 2, emphasizing the role played by adopting an Agile mindset. We detail our methodology in Sect. 3, where we present our research questions, data collection and analysis processes. Our main observations are discussed in Sect. 4, while the threats to our study’s validity are discussed in Sect. 5. Finally, we put our work into context using Sect. 6, with Sect. 7 dedicated to presenting our conclusions and future work ideas.

2 Key Elements of Software Engineering Projects

2.2 Team Project Course Description
In education, an Agile mindset is adopted in two ways. On one side, Agile practices are introduced as part of software engineering courses, making students implement them in developing real software applications. On the other side, learning and teaching practices are adapted to follow Agile values and principles, improving learning outcomes.
Both directions were followed in implementing the Team Project course. As part of the third year of study, students in Computer Science and Mathematics and Computer Science educational tracks are required to develop a software system of their choice, working in project teams of 10 members(on average), during the first semester of their third academic year. The number of teams formed in each year depends on student enrollment and organization, but usually it is between 45 and 50. The course is 14 weeks long and takes place from October to January.
Starting from 2017, with the purpose to improve collaboration between team members and to heighten the quality of the delivered product, we integrated experienced mentors from the local software industry. Each student team is assigned such a mentor who helps them organize, collaborate and embrace the Agile mindset, no matter which was the development methodology selected by the team at project onset. Whenever it is needed, the mentor also plays the role of the customer (or the role of Product Owner, if the chosen methodology is Scrum), in order to give the team a better perspective of how a final user would see their solution. Usually, each mentor is assigned to coordinate two or three teams of students.
As software project themes selected for implementation usually there are internship or volunteer management tools, learning management systems, educational quizzes, e-commerce solutions, video games and systems for the management of personal finances.
In parallel with the development of their software projects, enrolled students attend four different half-day workshops. Two of these workshops are focused on solution development and product mindset (Agile Software Development and Entrepreneurship) while the other two target soft skills (Communication and Presentation skills).
The Agile Software Development workshop discusses the Agile mindset (values, principles and way of thinking in an Agile context) and two important Agile methodologies: Scrum and Kanban. Most of the teams have already selected their development methodology when attending this workshop, based on their mentor’s suggestion. Still, during the workshop they have the opportunity to better understand the relevance of the Agile approach in building valuable software projects and discover new practices to implement within their effort.
At the end of the 14-week semester, a demo day is organized in which each team presents the result of their work in a 15-min live demonstration session. This is carried out in front of a faculty committee composed of senior teaching staff specialized in software engineering, who assign a grade to each of the teams. Within each team, student grades are decided by the mentors, based on each team member’s contribution and such that the average of team member grades fits the grade assigned to the team by the teaching staff.
The distinctive characteristics of the course are:
– Project based: the software system to be developed represents the kernel of the course and also the main evaluation criterion.
– Real-life: the system solves a real-life problem, and real-life project management is simulated as the team is supervised by a mentor, who is an experienced professional from partner software companies.
– Teamwork: students organize teams internally according to their choice and work in the same team for the entire duration of the semester.
– Evidence based: all performed activities correspond to set milestones and must be documented.
– Freedom of Choice: students are encouraged and have to decide both the software methodology and the technology stack, including programming languages, application architecture, employed frameworks and tools for project management and version control.
Learning objectives are focused on practical competencies acquired by students, which include the knowledge and skills necessary to implement and follow through an Agile software development process, adapting the life cycle of a software project to an Agile context and improving team communication and collaboration skills. The data used in this study corresponds to the academic year 2019–2020, when 492 students, forming 47 teams and 15 mentors were involved. The semester was not affected by the subsequent pandemic-related restrictions.

3 Research Methodology

3.1 Research Objectives
We adopted the Goal-Question-Metric approach as defined in [15] as our study’s guiding methodology. The main objective was to carry out a “qualitative investigation of the students’ perception regarding the adoption of Agile practices in team projects”. We projected the objective into three main research questions, some of which were further divided into more fine grained ones, as follows:
RQ1: How do students adopt an Agile mindset in their working process? Agile methodologies imply different practices related to software development and a successful adoption of Agile values, principles and practices depends on changing traditional practices. As a consequence, we planned to investigate: RQ1.1: How are Agile values and principles adopted by students? and RQ1.2: Which Agile practices are implemented by students in their working processes?
RQ2: What were the main challenges that students had to deal with? We aimed to analyse which were the main challenges, both technical and soft skills related, as described by the students themselves. These answers can offer important feedback in order to improve course content and project management during the semester.
RQ3: How did students manage the adoption of Agile practices? We wanted to evaluate the degree of Agile practices adoption, in order to have a better picture of what kind of Agile practices students have learned, both from their own self assessment and their mentors perspective. We divided this question into the following two sub-questions: RQ3.1: How did students evaluate their own process of learning Agile practices? and RQ3.2: How did mentors evaluate the adoption of Agile practices?
Qualitative analysis based on open coding was applied to data collected from students in order to provide answers to these research questions. We also collected mentor feedback through surveys. Data collection and data analysis is described in the following sections.

3.2 Data Collection
The data for this research was collected within the academic year 2019–2020, in the form of surveys that were completed by 47 student teams and questionnaires that were completed by 8 of the mentors. The questionnaires, responses from students and mentors are available within a replication package [12].
Student Surveys. A survey was designed consisting of four questions, as depicted in Fig. 1, which was then used to generate data for the corresponding four perspectives. Each team was expected to discuss the feedback internally and the team leader then submitted the result; one response per team was registered, based on agreement of opinions between team members. The survey also collected data about team name, project name and a short description of the project. All answer fields were free text, and students were encouraged to provide detailed information.
Mentor Feedback. Practitioners from partner companies who acted as mentors for the teams were asked to fill in a questionnaire at the end of the semester, after the projects were evaluated. The questions targeted student performance, challenges within the team and major outcomes of the course, as recommended in [8].

3.3 Data Analysis
Agile Mindset Adoption in Student Team Projects 293
 Fig. 1. Structure of the survey.
As our data collection strategy consisted of administering a survey comprised of a set of four questions with the answers provided in the form of free text without restrictions of length, we decided that the most suitable qualitative analysis method was open coding [4,6]. The steps corresponding to the open coding process are represented in Fig. 2. 47 out of the 49 teams provided answers for the four questions (see Fig. 1), each question being considered as a perspective in our analysis. For this study, the perspective associated to “Planning” did not provide meaningful information, so we did not take it into consideration in the present work. For each question, two of the authors performed the initial two steps of coding. The process is depicted in Fig. 2, where the steps are marked in circles, and the considered number of initial, respectively merged topics are represented in rectangles. Step 1 consisted in detecting the keywords and establishing the labels, while step 2 involved determining the topics, which means that the topics have been classified according to labels based on their semantics. The third author had the role of the third independent coder performing the task of merging these labels as step 3. These results were then discussed between the authors and a consensus was reached between initial topics, merged topics and labels for each perspective.
An entire document analysis was performed, examining each response and paragraph in detail, which enabled breaking the data into discrete ideas, actions and experiences. During the coding process we focused on:
– Identifying labels: based on terminology from software development and project management practices as described in the literature [2];
– Determining initial topics: based on text processing to eliminate duplicates and ambiguities;
– Merging topics in order to construct more general concepts. For example, student responses mentioned “task distribution”, “task prioritization”, “task management”, which were all merged to “task management” as being the most comprehensive topic.
The results for each perspective are presented in the following tables, containing labels, topics and suggestive examples from students responses. The student quotes are anonymized and indexed in order to support easy access as follows: T4.WR represents the response given by team 4 to the working process (W) question, labelled with roles (R).

4 Answers to RQs

RQ1: How do Students Adopt an Agile Mindset in Their Working Process? We wanted to make a clear distinction between the roles, practices and tools that were used by the project teams and the values and principles that stayed behind them. This is the reason why we created two subsequent research questions: one referring to the Agile values that were followed by the project teams (RQ1.1 How are Agile values and principles adopted by students?) and another one that took into account the implementation of a particular Agile methodology (RQ1.2 Which Agile practices are implemented by students in their working processes?)
Table 1 summarizes the labels, topics and examples corresponding to the working process perspective. Four main concepts were inferred as a result of applying open coding in this part of the survey: the habits and artifacts that are linked with Agile values, the applied development methodology, the roles assigned to team members, and tools that were used by the teams.

RQ1.1: How are Agile Values and Principles Adopted by Students? 32 teams explicitly declared that they approached their projects in an Agile way. However, there is an important distinction between doing Agile (meaning implementing specific Agile practices, methodologies or frameworks) and being Agile (meaning embracing the Agile values and principles as they were described in the Agile Manifesto). In this respect, we analyzed the answers from the last perspective, identifying those situations where we found discrepancies between the intention and the outcome in Agile adoption.
A careful investigation revealed that in some cases, even if the students declared to have an Agile approach, their responses actually described a waterfall way of thinking. As an example, upfront design was adopted by four teams and this comes in contradiction with building emergent designs in an incremental and iterative way: “the first couple of weeks was mostly dedicated to the engineering of the layers and architecture” (T5.WM) or “but in the end [of the first project stage] we had our almost complete structure and plan” (T18.WM). The last example also contradicts the fourth value of the Agile Manifesto, since it refers to building a complete up-front plan in the beginning of the project.
As we observed when we analyzed the roles played by students in their teams, more than half of project teams stated that they divided the team into backend and frontend sub-teams, each sub-team working on its assigned tasks. This has a negative impact in following the first value of the Agile Manifesto, where the collaboration and interaction between all team members is considered very important. The application of this value often drives to cross-functional and self-organized teams with team members working together during the project lifecycle and not being divided based on their technical abilities.
Moreover, this way to organize the team in frontend, backend and sometimes in database and testing sub-teams leads to focus on finishing horizontal slices of software project features, while the second value of the Agile Manifesto recommendation is to focus on finishing vertical working slices of the project.
Given that students used free text for responses we divide our findings based on the relation with the aforementioned values of the Agile Manifesto.
	
V1. Individuals and Interactions over Processes and Tools: We identified a number of eight teams that exposed self-organizing procedures in their working process: “brainstorming”, “efficient organization”, “interact” (T37.WV), “We held daily meetings” (T22.WV) “several times a week, we discussed what we did, what we will do and what problems we encountered” (T24.WV). We appreciated the desire of teams to learn, as training was labeled in seven team answers (“first ticket was associated to different learning activities”, T17.WV) and mentoring (“We scheduled workshops, where some of our more experienced colleagues held training sessions for the rest of the team”, T14.WV). One team was identified as having dysfunctional teamwork (“I’ll tried... but the team mates mostly ignored me”, T43.WV), while another team emphasized the importance of a friendly environment (“gave feedback and tried to keep the atmosphere as friendly as possible”, T24.WV).

V2. Working Software over Comprehensive Documentation: We observed that eight teams declared they measured their progress counting the number of working features built (“we’ve clearly stated... which features needed to be implemented”, T26.WV), and three other teams explicitly mentioned that the implemented process was followed in order to build intermediary working software (“[the process] focuses on the goal of delivering working software frequently”, T27.WV, “...the implementation of small modules/functionalities and then we thoroughly tested them, building-up on working software”, T33.WV). Only three teams mentioned documentation as a specific activity in their team (“we allocated a little more time to research, documentation and concept”, T33.WV), all of them referring to technical documentation. We deduced that customer documentation (user manual) was usually developed at the final stages of application development, just before presenting it in front of the faculty committee.

V3. Customer Collaboration over Contract Negotiation: Our analysis did not reveal strong connections between student team approaches and the third value of the Agile Manifesto. This happened mainly because the project theme was selected by the students themselves, so very often they played both the development and customer roles. Therefore, there was no clear distinction between the development tasks and customer collaboration activities, the customer satisfaction being mentioned just in those few cases when the mentor played the customer role. Only one team mentioned Minimum Viable Product, thinking of what could be the smallest set of features to bring value to the final customer (“build the process of the app in such a way that we can have a MVP as soon as possible”, T34.WV).

V4. Responding to Change over Following a Plan: As revealed by student responses, in most of the cases activities were oriented on iterations (or sprints), tasks or features. A number of 11 teams used sprint-driven planning (“we aimed to have at the end of each sprint a working version of the software”, T28.WV, “At the beginning of the sprints we had planning sessions”, T18.WV), seven teams made task oriented planning (“we created and choose the tasks each of us would have to do”, T5.WV), while six teams had feature oriented planning: “Though we didn’t succeed in implementing all the features we talked about at the beginning” (T32.WV). Two student teams expected that they will face some changes in requirements during the project lifecycle (“...to be able to change the requirements then when the situation demands it”, T50.WV), and one team declared that the requirements were pretty unclear at the beginning of the project (“we did not know in advance exactly what we want to implement”, T3.WV).

RQ1.2: Which Agile Practices Are Implemented by Students in Their Working Processes? Methodologies: Agile methodologies were adopted by most teams, as 15 teams mentioned Agile (“As an organization methodology I used Agile”, T16.WM), 10 others mentioned Scrum, respectively 5 mentioned Kanban, and 2 teams used Feature Driven Development. Other teams adopted an iterative way of developing software but they did not explicitly mention the methodology used (“we split our available time for development in sprints”, T4.WM). One team decided to use a custom tailored methodology (“we defined our own Agile methodology”, T20.WM).

Roles: 26 teams stated that they divided the team into backend and frontend sub-teams (“the tasks were divided... into backend and frontend tasks”, T4.WR, “to allow parallel development on backend and frontend”, T38.WR), 10 teams had an assigned role for testing (“members responsible with testing”, T30.WR), while six teams acknowledged the role of the Scrum master: “each sub-team had its own Scrum master”, T36.WR. A set of other roles were mentioned, either functional or non-functional, including IT support, documentation, or team leader.

Tools: Teams used several tools as part of project implementation. They can be classified in tools for source control such as Github, GitLab or Bitbucket and task management tools such as Trello or Discord.

Label
Agile Values (label WV)
Agile Methodologies (label: WM)
Roles (identified roles in the team) (label: WR)
Tools (label: WT)
Topics
Examples
“gave feedback and tried to keep the atmosphere as friendly as possible”, “we allocated a little more time to research, documentation and concept”, “We have learned to make constructive reviews and learn from the feedback we receive”, “respecting our client’s requirements”, “We went back and forth with several idea proposals”
“The methodology used in development, that was implemented by the team is Feature-Driven Development”, “As a methodology we tried to be Agile by applying a Scrum process”, “We went with a Kanban way”
“X took responsibility for the backend”, “groups that worked on different tasks: mobile application, backend development, testing, documentation”
“Github”, “GitLab”, “BitBucket”, “Discord”
Agile Mindset Adoption in Student Team Projects 297 Table 1. Labels for “Working process” (open coding redone based on [13]).
    Stand-up, feedback, self organize, communication, frequent releases, documentation, incremental, reviews, continuous delivery, iterations, sprints, deadlines
  Scrum, Kanban, Feature driven development
  Backend/frontend, project manager, product owner, requirements engineer, devops, testing, IT support, technical leader, documentation, reviewer, team leader, scrum master, AI
  Source control tools and task management tools


RQ2: What Were the Main Challenges That Students Had to Deal With? The challenges that students faced and tried to overcome can be grouped into three main types: organizational, technical and related to soft skills, as shown in Table 2. In order to have the full picture, we incorporated mentor feedback, illustrated in Table 3, into our analysis.

Organizational Challenges: 16 teams considered the hardest challenge to be task management (“Challenge: create and detail tasks to be easily understood”, T2.CO) or time management (“one challenge was intense work in last days to finish project”, T10.CO). Summarizing, either tasks or time have put pressure on project development for approximately 68% of the teams. Eight teams faced technology choice as the main challenge: “main issues was to decide which tools and frameworks to use” (T14.CO).

TechnicalChallenges: More than half of the teams (53%) dealt with technical problems, in some part due to lack of technical knowledge (“a more messy challenge was learning new frameworks and libraries on the go”, T2.CT), or due to incorrect project management (“Our challenge arose when, after starting our implementation, we frequently needed to change the DB schema and relations, thus indirectly forcing everyone to do the same updates”, T28.CT).

Soft Skills Challenges: the extent of each team member’s involvement was the main problem for 10 of the teams: “Being able to motivate everyone to work consciously and constantly” (T5.CS). Five teams were confronted with communication problems: “biggest challenges that we encountered were communication with the team members, ... and the communication with the mentor” (T18.CS).

Organizational (label: CO)
Technical (label: CT)
Soft skills (label: CS)
Topics
Table 2. Labels for “Challenges” [13]. Examples
“synchronizing as a team and working together”, “decide which tools and frameworks to use”, “finish everything before the deadline”
“learn to use the technologies”, “how to combine what we worked on”, “over-engineering in some places”
“Being able to motivate everyone to work consciously and constantly”, “it was way harder for everyone to keep in touch with everyone”, “organizing and coordinating”
   Time management, task management, teamwork, collaboration, technology choice
  Technical skills, effective collaboration, over-engineering
  Involvement, communication, collaboration, teamwork
   Table 3. Mentor feedback on 10 common issues in team projects and the relevant Agile values that are influenced. Scores recorded on a 1 (not likely at all) to 5 (very likely) scale, including standard deviation (σ) (adapted from [13]).
 Challenge
Lack of engagement from team members
Student task knowledge and assumption Miscommunication within the team Problems with time management
Team leader dictates what team members do Lack of technical expertise
Dividing the work among team members
Work is carried out by one or two team members Conflicts among team members
No one wants to act as team leader
Values V1 V4 V1 V4 V1
–
V1, V2 V1
V1
V1
Mean σ 3.62 1.30 3.50 0.53 3.25 1.03 3.25 0.88 2.87 1.24 2.87 1.12 2.50 1.41 2.37 1.3 2.37 1.4 2.12 1.45
           

One team declared that they had no challenges worth mentioning, and that the ones that appeared were easily solved, while two other teams (T12, T24) did not complete this part of the survey.

Mentor Feedback: Table 3 shows the mentor’s answers regarding some of the most common challenges in the team projects [8]. The most significant highlighted challenge was the lack of engagement from team members, for which mentors reported a mean score of 3.62, with 3 out of 8 respondents attributing it the maximum value on a 5point scale. Another significant issue regarded communication and the assumption of project roles and tasks within teams. We note the low value of the standard deviation (σ = 0.53), which shows agreement among the mentors. Mentor feedback was mostly positive regarding the existence of team conflicts, or for the presumed case of students not wanting to assume coordination responsibilities. In most cases, we observe a value of σ ≥ 1, which shows that the prevalence of issues still varied among the teams.
We were also interested in a cross-sectional exploration of challenges as perceived by students versus mentors. In this regard, our answer to RQ2 shows alignment between student and mentor perception. On one hand, challenges were an important motivator of progress; we believe that agreement between student and mentor perceptions represents an important indicator of effective communication and team progress.


 Label
Acquired knowledge
Good practices
Topics
Agile Mindset Adoption in Student Team Projects 299 Table 4. Labels for “Lessons learned” [13].
Examples
“We learned ... teamwork and the ability to support and help each other”, “We have learned to make constructive reviews and learn from the feedback we receive”, “We learned mostly about the efficiency of the SCRUM methodology, about teamwork and time management”
“Communication is Key”, “we have learnt is how hard it is to motivate people, and to manage a team of 9 people”, “task management is crucial”
   Teamwork, technical skills, communication, estimation, collaboration, code review, SCRUM, time management, version control system, task management
  Communication, motivation, teamwork, project management


Most of the common challenges identified by mentors were connected with the first value of the Agile Manifesto. At the same time, the third value was not represented in this list most probably because the teams themselves played both the customer and developer roles, so the communication and interaction with the customer were not approached in an explicit manner. In addition, there was the challenge regarding the lack of technical expertise that had no direct connection with any of the Agile values.

RQ3: How Did Students Manage the Adoption of Agile Practices? Students had the freedom to employ a project development methodology of their own choice. Issues related to planning, working process and lessons learned were reported in detail within our precursor work [13]. The present paper is specifically focused on the process and experience of adopting Agile methodologies. 32 out of the 47 participating teams stated that they approached their project in an Agile way. We focused our evaluation on them. We employed the free text feedback from the student and mentor questionnaires together with the results of the open coding process. However, as already reported in our answer to RQ1.1, we did note a few discrepancies. Several teams stated using an Agile approach but instead described a waterfall process. As such, we expected most teams to show a partial adoption of Agile practices, limited to those that students were familiar with or felt they better suited the project. This provides an opportunity to understand the students’ perception of the importance and suitability of Agile practices and provide more focused training that covers areas of uncertainty. We provide our answer to RQ3 by first evaluating the students’ own feedback, followed by that of the mentors, who also reported on the progress teams achieved during the semester.

RQ3.1: How Did Students Evaluate Their Own Process of Learning Agile Practices? We used the student responses to our questionnaire to identify the Agile practices employed by each team, and use Fig. 3 to represent our findings. Out of the 47 teams that responded to our questionnaire, 32 specifically mentioned using Agile. Our analysis of the student responses however identified Agile practices being used by 44 teams, representing 93% of the responding teams. We divide them into Roles, Ceremonies/Practices and Artifacts and use Fig. 3 to highlight only those that were reported by at least one of the teams.
In the Roles category, we observe that 26 out of the 44 reporting teams mentioned team member roles or that they worked as a self-organizing team. Only 2 teams reported having a product owner and 10 a Scrum master. None of them mentioned the product backlog, which we feel is an important piece of the Scrum framework.
With regards to Ceremonies/Practices, the most often reported ones are sprints and iterations (24 teams), together with standup (12 teams) and planning (8 teams) ceremonies. As expected, this data was biased towards aspects previously practiced by students during previous coursework, which required feature planning over several iterations. We also observed a number of other practices that were seldom and inconsistently used within teams.
When it came to artifacts, we found that 27 teams used task boards, making them and team organization the most prevalent practices. The open coding process allowed us to go into more detail and identify common trends within the student responses. An example of this is shown in Table 4, which presents some of the open coding topics discovered. We divided them into acquired knowledge and good practices.
We observed that 12 teams explicitly mentioned the importance of teamwork, which was also the subject of one organized workshop. Several aspects were identified to be important such as “we all agreed that in the end we learned how to be a team” (T16), “teamwork makes the dream work” (T33), or in more detail “we saw how to work in a team, similar to a working place (responsibilities, targets, deadlines)” (T9) [13]. Many teams also identified the importance of communication: “we communicated a lot throughout all the development stages” (T32), “The project represented a valuable exercise in improving communication” (T45). Learning and adaptability were also highlighted by several teams: “learn by listen to team mates opinions”, (T6), “We have learned to make constructive reviews and learn from the feedback we receive”, (T11), “adapt to others’ needs” (T15) and “adapt to several ways of problem solving” (T38). Finally, task management was also identified as an important practice: “During the implementation of our software solution, we were taught that ... task management is crucial” (T27).

RQ3.2: How Did Mentors Evaluate the Adoption of Agile Practices? We synthesized the feedback from the mentor questionnaire into Tables 3 and 5. We focus the present section on the evaluation of Agile practices. A generic discussion regarding the mentors’ feedback is available within our precursor work [13]. We linked the challenges most often reported by mentors with the four Agile values as presented in our answer to RQ1.1. First of all, we observed that none of the challenges were linked to Agile value V3 (Customer collaboration over contract negotiation). The reason can be explained by perusing Fig. 3, which shows that only two teams discussed the Product Owner role. In the remaining teams, this role was jointly assumed, as the teams themselves settled on the project topic and jointly carried out task planning and allocation. Likewise, while the lack of technical knowledge represented an important hurdle for many teams, it could not be directly linked with any of the four Agile values and therefore remained unassigned.
We observed most of the encountered challenges to be linked with V1 (Individuals and interactions over processes and tools). As detailed in our precursor work [13] as well as the answers to the previous research questions, most challenges were linked to team communication and motivation. We note that out of the four challenges most often reported by mentors, two were linked with the V1 Agile value, and two with the V4 value (Responding to change over following a plan). We note the existence of agreement between the evaluations by mentors and the students themselves regarding the most prevalent issues.
With regards to progress, Table 5 shows the mentors’ evaluation within four key areas critical for successful project completion. In all areas, we note the value of the standard deviation σ ≈ 1, which illustrates differences between the mentors’ perception. We also note that all mentors evaluated that progress had taken place, as progress in all key areas was evaluated with at least 2 points.

5 Threats to Validity
We designed, organized and carried out our study according to well-known best practices [14]. Surveys were sent to all student teams and guiding mentors after the course was completed and the evaluation had taken place. The paper’s first author was responsible for coordinating the course. Both co-authors are experienced in project management and software engineering, both in academia as well as industry. The major steps carried out included setting up the questionnaire structure and collection methodology, processing free-text responses using open coding, analyzing and interpreting the results and putting them into the proper context.
We addressed internal threats by involving researchers with experience in teaching, software engineering and the transformative effects of adopting Agile methodologies. Student and mentor questionnaires were validated before being handed out. Open coding work was carried out in pairs, with the third researcher assuming a validation role and ensuring that consensus was reached regarding assigned labels and their interpretation. In addition, we revisited and validated the labelling process presented in the precursor study [13].
The most important external threats identified related to the context in which the case studies took place, namely course curricula, requirements, team size and organization as well as the means and the moment of reporting. We identified and used relevant related work to establish our study’s methodology, including questionnaire structure and contents as well as the key areas our research was focused on. One of the authors had no involvement with the course’s structure or activities, and their input was used to control bias. When compared to the precursor study [13], we focused on those soft skills aspects relevant for the adoption of Agile methodologies. We confirmed that our results were in line with those from existing literature [1,5,16].

7 Conclusions and Future Work
The present work represents a detailed follow-up of our initial investigation regarding how students perceived the importance and impact that soft skills have on the development of complex software projects [13]. We extended our work to specifically cover the adoption and impact of Agile methodologies, as they appeared to be prevalent in the student feedback gathered during our initial study.
We analyzed student and mentor feedback gathered in the form of free-text answers to corresponding questionnaires and took into account the results of the final project evaluation. These were carried out during live sessions where student teams presented their work in front of an experienced faculty committee. Like in the case of our initial evaluation [13] we employed open-coding in order to tag and classify the feedback of course participants; when compared with our initial investigation, we examined both student and mentor feedback in relation to the adoption of an Agile working process and benefits tangible to its adopters. We observed that many teams were challenged by the technical prowess required to lead their project towards a successful conclusion, as team members had varying levels of expertise with the required tools and frameworks. Several teams organized internal “workshops“ where these issues were resolved using communication and teamwork; however, we also noticed instances where team members remained dissatisfied with the level of motivation and involvement in their teams.
Our initial investigation [13] already covered project planning, the working process and the alignment between student and mentor evaluation. As such, we devised three new research questions focused on the main subject of the present evaluation. The first two were focused on the adoption and evaluation of an Agile mindset, while the last one targeted the evaluation of the main challenges faced by students. We dedicated Sect. 4 to a detailed discussion of the results. We observed that most teams incorporated Agile ideas or methods into their working process; we also discovered instances where students claimed Agile adoption that was contradicted by their own detailed reporting. 
As future work, we aim to support student teams regarding the adoption of an Agile mindset in a more focused way. We also aim to incentivise teams to foster continuous collaboration and motivation at team level. In addition, extending our investigation to cover several consecutive academic years remains one of our important interests; this is especially true since course activities were moved fully online for the 2020–2021 academic year as a result of the pandemic-related measures. In this context, we aim to investigate what impact the fully online work environment has on soft skill development and teamwork, as well as carry out a comparison between offline and online course organization.

