Interdisciplinary Agile Teaching

Abstract—This innovative practice paper describes a projectbased group work where conversion master students developed the skills required for agile software development methods. There are many examples of agile methods taught in, for instance, capstone courses in software engineering programmes. It has been shown to be a popular and beneficial method of learning. However, most agile teams in the software industry are made up of members with different educational backgrounds (i.e. not just software developers, as there will also business analysts, designers, testers etc.). Such a diversity of roles might be beneficial in teaching agile methods in an academic setting.
This reflective educational paper describes the evolution of an industry sourced problem-based agile student project, which over three successive years has included students from three different faculties. Although the experience has broadly been positive each year, this paper describes and reflects on both the good and problematic observations that the teaching staff has made over the years. The changes of the projects has been based by reflecting on these insights. These reflections are described and several recommendations are drawn from the experiences.
These include, that it is important that the cohorts collaborate and work together in parallel. Individual groups, of diverse cohorts, should work in isolation. It is important to have industrial partners who are participating actively in the process, and it is important to not underestimate the work that is required by the academics to coordinate the projects to make them successful.

Index Terms—Agile Software Development, Teaching Agile, Problem-based Pedagogy.


I. INTRODUCTION
Since the beginning of the 1990s, there has been a dramatic increase in jobs within the information and communication technology (ICT) sector in New Zealand (NZ) [1] with numerous ICT related positions on the skilled occupations and immediate skill shortage lists used for visa applications into NZ [2], [3]. In the School of Engineering and Computer Science at Victoria University of Wellington (VUW), it is not uncommon to see students leaving the Bachelor of Engineering or the Bachelor of Science prematurely because they have secured jobs in the local IT industry [4].
In July 2015, the NZ government announced the establishment of three ICT Graduate Schools spread across the
country. They had determined that the traditional universities of NZ were not preparing sufficient numbers of graduates for the growing ICT industry. One of the ICT graduate Schools was awarded to a consortium of tertiary education institutions [5], this consortium included the programmes that will be discussed in this paper.
The School had studied 71 local industries and their expectations of recent IT graduates finding that ”soft-skills”, such as communication and teamwork, were an especially sought-after quality with several companies reporting that they have even employed non-ICT trained students with those soft-skills expecting to train them in-house [6]. Furthermore, prominent local companies are increasingly adopting agile development methods [7], where teams from various professional backgrounds, such as programmers, business analysts, user experience experts, commonly collaborate to solve problems, which increase the need for such soft skills and understanding of what other professions do.
This paper describes an agile group work exercise that combined three different programmes in an agile learning experience where the groups worked on industry sourced problems. The group work has run over three years and has changed significantly over these years. The changes have been made based on reflective analysis by the teaching staff based on observations made during the projects. This reflective research paper describes the underlying reflections based on observations and feedback that has led to the evolution of the agile group work and analyses this changes and concludes with several recommendations for teaching agile development methods in this environment.
Section II reviews some general issues to be aware of when teaching agile methods using group work. Section III describes the method of reflective analysis used in this paper. Section Iv presents how agile group-based learning has evolved the last three years at the ICT graduate school in Wellington, while section V presents, discusses and reflects upon observations made by the teaching team while teaching this. Section VI concludes by drawing out recommendations from the discussion.


III. REFLECTIVE ANALYSIS METHOD
The agile project has evolved over time based on evaluation by the teaching staff. This research has therefore not had a clear plan from the start of this process. The underpinning evaluation method used was based on reflective analysis of observations made by the teaching staff. For formative purpose, such as improvement of courses over time, it is generally considered best practice to follow this method instead of using quantitative tools, such as students’ questionnaires, which are better at assessing individual teacher performance than improving course quality over time [20].
Following this methodology there are four types of data that are used for reflection, these are feedback from students, self-generated feedback, feedback from colleagues and incidental feedback [20]. All of these have been used as sources for reflection, although self-generated and peer feedback is the core sources.
The students have been given the chance to provide feedback orally on the agile projects during the project phase. However, this work was initially not intended as a research project, but developed as a teaching experience into a research project that produced valuable lessons, therefore ethical approval was not sought to disclose the students’ comments, as a consequence these are not quoted directly in this work, however the students’ feedback has influenced the reflections of the teaching staff and will be described indirectly in places.
None of the compulsory end-of-trimester summative student feedback surveys required by VUW have been used to inform this work, mostly because these are surveying performance of teaching staff rather than course quality, but also because the scores have been continuously ’excellent’ or ’very good’ although based on a very small data sets (between 4-6 students), which significantly limits the value of results, and therefore could only distort the understanding of the course by presenting it in a too positive light with little statistical significance.
The course has each year been taught by a team of academics who have as a team discussed observations critically, with the aim to improve the course over time. This is the main source of data for reflection together with self-generated feedback grounded in the day to day support of students by each individual academic. The reflection has been done following Gibbs’ reflective cycle [21] as a guideline to describe the evolution of the agile projects. Therefore in the next chapter the changes are described and in the following chapter the feeling, evaluation and analysis is described for each year to explain the changes. In the final section the main conclusions and recommendations are drawn from the reflection throughout progression of the course over time.


IV. EDUCATIONAL SETTING FOR THIS AGILE LEARNING EXPERIENCE
This section presents how the agile development teaching project has evolved over the last three years at the ICT graduate school in Wellington, table I shows the progression over the years. The reflections on those years are in the following section where the reasoning behind the changes is presented.
   The group project was first run as part of the course “Software Development Studio II” (SWEN503). It is the last taught course on the Master of Software Development (SwDev) that has now been delivered for three years within the ICT Graduate School in Wellington. The SwDev is a conversion master, i.e. a master that admits students into another field than their previous learning and teaches them a new field, therefore this master teaches students, who have bachelor degrees outside computer science and IT, software engineering, including programming [22].
The learning objectives of the course include advanced professional practice skills, e.g. software development methodologies and software project planning. In each of the years, this has involved group projects where the students were expected to use and learn agile development practices. In the first year, 22 students did this course. They worked on three different projects lasting three weeks each. There were four groups which worked on two different industry projects with an industrial product owner.
In the second year students from the course ”Web Design” as part of the Master of User Experience (UX) joined this group work. The course learning objectives in this course include integration of Web design skills, software, and practice and critical application of them to solve design problems, construction of creative strategies to address Web design challenges, and demonstration of the ability to research and implement Web design tools independently. This year, 29 SwDev and 5 UX students worked on one project lasting three weeks and the SwDev students did an extra three weeks on another agile group project. Each iteration had five groups, and there were three industrial product owners in each iteration.
In the third year as shown in table II, the course ”Digital Innovation and Strategy” taught as part of the Master of Professional Business Analysis (BA) joined the projects alongside the ”Communication Design” and ”Web Design” UX courses. 11 industrial problems had been sourced from start-up companies. To allow for different teaching schedules in the three different programmes the BA had a leading role while working with the UX students for two weeks followed by two weeks where the UX led with support from the BA students. During these four weeks, the SwDev students provided support to the groups during meetings where they were expected to provide critical feedback and questions for consideration. This resulted in documentation describing digital product/service/business model based on the initial business problem. For the following three weeks five of the projects were selected by the SwDev students and together with the UX students, they developed minimal viable products (MVP), while the BA students were expected to provide feedback and input throughout this process. The BA students were also involved in the MVP demonstrations at the end of the projects, by assessing how the MVP matched the product owners’ acceptance criteria that were laid out in the design activities.
TABLE II
ROLES PROGRESSION OVER THE PROJECT WEEKS IN THE THIRD YEAR
Years Cohorts
2016-2017 SwDev
2017-2018 SwDev, UX
2018-2019 SwDev, UX, BA
 Leading cohort Supporting cohort
1-2 3-4 5-7
  BA UX
UX BA UX
SwDev
TABLE I COHORTS BY YEAR
Weeks

Prior to starting this learning experience, there were concerns that the projects could turn into a waterfall type project. To avoid this the SwDev and UX students where allowed and expected to, if necessary, change any aspect of the work from the previous round with the requirement of including the product owners in this process. There were also several feedback opportunities throughout the projects where the various student cohorts were expected to engage critically with the other groups.
Prior to starting the agile projects, each cohort had training in agile development. The SwDev students had a week where they learned about various agile methods and gained practical experience through small practical exercises. The BA students had several seminars on agile development and the UX students learned about design sprint, facilitation and collaboration. All three cohorts were invited to a half-day session where they learned about Kanban using the board game getKanban [23].

V. SELF-REFLECTION AND DISCUSSION
This section presents a discussion and a reflection on the experiences by the teaming team and how this evolved the agile projects over the years.

A. First year: Software developers working together
The overall experience of the projects was good. There were a limited number of group issues and the industrial partners where all engaged actively. It seemed that from a student perspective the biggest issue was that the structure of the course meant that they did 9 weeks of group work that was only broken up by the Christmas break. This meant that they for a long period only had contact through supervision with the academic staff. This meant that they felt isolated in the group work and a few students reported a need for pastoral care in that period [22]. There was some notions of feeling stressed by the constant need for performance including weekend work. Although the course was not designed to use the weekends the students pushed each other in their teams to achieve as well as possible and that probably introduced a level of peer pressure that did increase the level of quality but also induced stress for some, especially the students with families or other special circumstances. It seemed that the students to some extent focused more on the product they were making than life/work balance, which should be part of a good agile working environment.
The industrial partner participation was good in all of the projects. They all met with the student groups at least twice per week and some of them met more often. Two of the projects shared the industrial partner and they worked on the same code base but from two different viewpoints solving independent problems. This was arranged to expose the students to agile development where multiple groups share the same code base. Both of the teams, however, found that their problem was impossible to solve, mostly because they found that their problem was interconnected to the other team and conflicts were too difficult to resolve. They also argued, and managed to convince the teaching staff, that the problems were too complex for the length of the project. Two separate problems were then defined in collaboration with the teaching staff and the product owner, which allowed a more separated approach. This resolved the issues and the teams did produce viable, although smaller, solutions to the initial problem.
From a teaching perspective, there were however several issues throughout the projects. There were several topics that had not been taught enough, or had not manifested as important to the students, throughout the year, which would need to be changed for the following year. This was the first year of the programme and because a conversion master was new to the school some topics had been expected to be learned as self-directed learning through deliverables for other topics. For instance, it became clear that relying on self-directed learning of software engineering tools was not sufficient because it meant that many of the students, were lacking a “language” to discuss software engineering problems. This was changed in the following years so that there was a week included in the programme focusing on traditional software engineering practices.
Related to this was that the students lacked knowledge about agile methods. SWEN503 included two days of taught agile
development and then expected the students to learn about these through practical experience. Although at the time it seemed like a good idea, it became clear that the students focused more on the industrial problem and finding a solution than learning and experimenting with agile methods. This is not to say that it did not happen, it just did not happen at the level that the teaching staff wanted and when the students submitted their work, their reflections seemed shallow on this aspect overall and most of them had only really used a few of the tools expected in agile development. Two days of teaching was apparently not enough for this and to improve this aspect it was agreed to include a one week agile methodology week in the following year.
One important aspect that was lacking was the multiple skills that are commonly present in group work. There was some of this present because the students had different educational backgrounds from their prior studies, but for many of the students, these were far removed from the traditional skills found in development teams, including musicians, psychologist, English majors, linguists etc. The common factor, namely software development, was the common culture in the groups, and although it was satisfying to observe that the students had developed into software developers, it meant the collaborative nature across disciplines within agile development was somewhat lost during these weeks, what united them was that they all knew programming. They had also with almost no exceptions worked together with each other in the past. Furthermore, the groups that had a student with a design or experiences in art or business analysis had advantages over the other groups. They were able to develop better looking or better-validated solutions to the problems.
Therefore the lead academic on this programme started to seek opportunities to involve students from other programmes to provide a more realistic group demography with various cohorts to give them experiences as close to industrially based agile teams as possible. After talking with the other programme directors within the ICT graduate school it became clear that it was only practical to include UX students into this exercise. This was due to programme differences in the delivery of topics and assignments. It was, therefore, the plan to merge groups with both SwDev and UX students in the projects the following year. It was also the assessment that the feeling of isolation would be limited by shortening the period and include other students. Furthermore more time was allocated for supervision.

B. Second year: Software developers and user experience students working together
Students from the two cohorts were introduced to the other members of their team and had an initial meeting with their industrial client. The UX students had a class prior to this session about teamwork and how to facilitate collaboration and design thinking workshops. While the SwDev students had one week of agile development. The two cohorts had not met prior to their introduction. Immediately after the introduction, the collaboration started. Some of the UX students facilitated the team to design wire-frames collaboratively, other designers chose to work in isolation and provided the team with wireframes, while the SwDev students worked on architecture and back-end development.
During the project, the UX students tested and iterated their wire-frames while working on high fidelity mock-ups and in some cases helping with front-end development, while the SwDev students were developing the designs. Most teams worked together in the studio full-time for the whole sprint, the designers were available to address issues in a timely manner and meet with the client. We noticed that teams who were highly collaborative and met with the client often were more successful in addressing challenges. The industrial partners were all very engaging during this period with one of them meeting daily and the others at least twice per week, which seemed to provide a good balance of actually working on the problem and getting feedback on the progress.
Some of the user experience design students were feeling stressed to create design quickly while learning about Lean UX and the development students were expecting highfidelity mock-ups to be delivered more quickly. Some of the development students felt their time would be more useful in development only rather than being part of the design process. We thought it might be good to respond to the feedback and divide this project into two phases, giving the design students more time to research and design, while the development students have more time for development. From this observation came the idea to provide the design students worked time on the research and design in collaboration, potentially, with business analysis students to create a report with research findings, business model, and high-fidelity mock-ups which would then be provided to the client and the software development students. To avoid a waterfall model it would be important to give the SwDev students opportunities for gaining insight and provide feedback during this process, while also allowing continued changes to the user experience and other documentation throughout the development phase.
After the combined project with SwDev and UX students, the SwDev student had a three-week agile development-only project based on 4 new ideas and the continuation of one of the previous ideas. In this phase, the industrial partners of 2 of the new ideas were travelling and had asked colleagues to step in and provide this support. These colleagues were both not working in the Wellington office, and they had also misunderstood the aim of the programme and what was expected of them. Therefore it was difficult for these two groups to get in contact with them and there seemed to be a certain disinterest in these projects from these substitute product owners. This was frustrating to the students in these two groups, it demotivated them and some of the students started focusing more on criticising the problems than actually working on them. Therefore one of the teaching staff had to step in and act as a product owner to provide guidance until the original product owners returned from their travel. This meant that the students were more focused on what did not work than how to get it to work. This reflects the importance
of active product owners who are in close proximity to the teaching facilities [9].
One of the groups was continuing the development of one of the previous projects. It included two of the original team members and three new. Including the old team member meant that they could teach the new members the code-base, while the new members provided critical feedback and new ideas. It became a highly productive project with a good quality product at the end.

C. Third year: Software developers, user experience and business analysis students working together
Kanban is a good tool to teach how an agile team should manage a project maximising the output (i.e in terms of monetary value in case of the Kanban game). Our experience with using the Kanban boardgame as a tool to introduce teach agile practices and fundamentals was generally encouraging. Furthermore it functioned as a good “ice breaker” for the participants that did not know each other. Our observations with the 8-9 teams playing the game confirmed the finding of [24] that ”Games introduce overhead, such as learning the rules and setting up the game and may require more time to complete than other methods”. However, it also provided a practical insight into some of the processes you have to go through when following agile methods.
Pragmatically to reflect the different programme structures of the three programmes, a structural compromise was found involving each cohort in three two week stages where two cohorts worked closely together on the projects at any given time with one of the cohorts taking a leading role. The third cohort would still be involved, however to a lesser extent and only at a few meetings.
The anticipation by the teaching team was that this could present a challenge where the process could foster a waterfall mindset among the students and especially in the development stages limit the SwDev student’s agile experience. To counteract this the teaching team made sure to mention and encourage good agile practices at any opportunity in class. Furthermore, the SwDev students were encouraged to change the specifications if they needed to do so, and all of the development teams had 2-3 UX students on their team to further develop or change mock-ups.
On reflection, the biggest issue with this schedule was actually not a waterfall problem. There were only two of the teams that were held back by the specification for a considerable time, therefore being “trapped” by the waterfall mindset, however, with guidance from the teaching staff they removed some of the constraints in the original specifications and arrived at a minimal viable product. The other groups changed specifications when needed.
The biggest issue with the scheduling was that there was a lack of ownership among the students. Because the SwDev students had not been an integrated part of developing the specifications they, rightly or wrongly, always started criticising the specifications whenever there were issues associated with them. Even when this was related to coding issues, it seemed easier to criticise the need for doing something in a specific way rather than take ownership and focus on solving the issues or finding alternative ways to solve it. They had not truly taken ownership of the problem. In the second year’s group-work, this had not been an issue because the UX and SwDev students collaborated throughout the design phases. In that process, some of the SwDev students criticised the design in the design phase and perhaps did not fully engage, however after they had been created they could not criticise them. This lack of ownership was also felt among the BA students. After the completion of the user research and of the design requirements, BA students and half of the UX cohort were not expected to play a major role during weeks 5 to 7 when the MVP would be developed. Some BA students considered that their mandate was over after week 5 and did not realize that their input would still be expected. This disconnect also created an incentive for the BA and UX students to frame their design artefacts (personas, user journeys, user stories board, functional and non-functional requirements) in a way that was consumable and relevant to the product owners rather than the SwDev students. While both audiences find value in these artefacts, they use those for different kinds of information and purposes. On reflection, it is very important to include all SwDev, BA, and UX students in all design and delivery phases of an agile project to avoid these issues.
There were also issues with the industrial partners because of the scheduling of the course. Because the process started with 11 problem statements and all of the 11 industrial partners knew that BA and UX students would work on these producing design specification and only five of these projects would go into development, it seemed, that the industrial partners focused on the design processes. They were engaged in this and met with BA and UX students throughout the process as required. However when the development process started out of the five projects that got selected only two of them continued participating in the development process.
Several factors could cause this distinction between the design and development phases happened. For instance, the project was ”sold” to the industrial partners from the perspective of them having an opportunity they would like to have studied with a guaranteed design and a potential MVP as a result. Furthermore, the Christmas break separated the two efforts so there was a natural break between design and development. In New Zealand, it is common to take a few extra weeks holiday in connection with the Christmas period for the summer vacation, several of the partners had done this, possibly because they saw more value in the design phase. In the previous years we also had this issue but none of the partners “disappeared”, because those years the emphasis was on the development of an MVP, and if the partner was travelling at least they had found stand in product owners (which introduced other issues, as explained above).
Finally, in the third year, there was also a three week project iteration with only SwDev students. During this project iteration two teams worked on one of the projects with active industrial partners from the first iteration. The other three
worked on a separate project with a partner who took part the previous year. The two teams working together worked without any major issues. In the other three groups, there were issues with missing three weeks (50%) of source code that had disappeared from the previous year’s group work due to server discontinuation. This disrupted the projects severely and the expectations had to be scaled back due to the lacking code. This was a frustrating time for the teams and it took time before they realised this issue because they were learning the legacy code using limited documentation.
For both the two and three team-based projects it seemed that a lot of the work happened in “super-teams”, i.e. 1015 students working on the same problem, instead of several teams working on several sub-problems. It seemed that the inexperience of the students made it hard to collaborate in several different teams using the same code-base, because this introduced a complexity that they were not prepared for, there were especially technical issues with merging conflicts and changing to functionalities that one group relied on. Furthermore, the learning and design necessary to start developing seemed to happen best in the larger group. However the “super-team” approach introduced added communication overhead and the effectivity of the teams dropped, event if it overcame some of the initial issues. It also limited the learning of agile development where teams usually are of a smaller size.
This tendency was also observed in the first year when two groups used the same codebase and it seems that the complexity for beginners to cope with intra-group development is too high for it to be expected.

D. Building Teams
Normally where creating teams we have used a distribution method where each team has a randomly selected top student (i.e. solid programming skills), a below-average-programming skills students, and some average-skilled students. This has been done to ensure that each team has leaders in programming who can help the other students. To avoid hot-shots versus discouraged teams [14]. For the first iteration this year the academic team assigned the group members in a way that the students were placed in the groups based on their academic performance so far in the programme. In other words, with only minor adjustments highly-achieving students were placed in a group, average students were assigned to one group, and so forth.
It was surprising that the middle group seemed more unhappy about the way in which the groups were formed than the other groups. They seemed to be thinking that they were “destined-to-fail” This was not reflected by the groups with the lower or higher overall academic performance. There might be two reasons for this. Firstly, there were some technical challenges within that group. This group had been assigned a project that seemed to use a restrictive technology where they, with good reason, could not get that technology working. Secondly, there seemed to be some social issues both within the group and with other groups. An agile team is a social entity [25] that requires intensive social activities by the different team members [26]. One of the issues we observed was that the academic grade difference between most of the students in the average group and their counterparts in the top groups was minimal. Thus, it seemed several members thought that they should have been in those higher groups and this was putting them off during the run of the project. This observation is supported by the fact that the lower achieving groups did not present any negative sentiment of this sort, in fact, one student commented that it was nice to be able to learn from teaching other students things that he could do, whereas in other groups this had not been a possibility.


VI. CONCLUSION AND RECOMMENDATIONS
The following subsections provide our conclusions and recommendations for teaching agile involving industrial partners and using multiple cohorts.
A. Cohorts should work in parallel
It is vital to have all cohorts collaborating from the beginning of the project. Every team member needs to have ownership feeling of the project otherwise a lot of energy is lost while criticising, rightly or wrongly, other people’s work. It might not be necessary to involve everybody equally as much during different phases, but everyone should be active in the processes.
B. Industrial partner participation is important
It is important to ensure that industrial partners can and will be actively engaged for the entirety of the projects. It is very demotivating for team members when the partners disappear and it also makes it difficult for the teams to make decisions if they cannot get hold of product owners.
It is equally problematic if a product owner decides to “outsource” their responsibilities for a period of the project to colleagues who are not well-informed about the project as this can be confusing for the students.
C. Academic programme leaders and industry engagement manager shouldn’t underestimate the coordination required
The live, agile projects involved over 70 students from three separate academic programmes. Cross-disciplinary projects that blend skills from SwDev, UX, and BA students demand close coordination among academic programme leaders. Finding appropriate hand-offs, interfaces, and touch-points between three programmes is a complex task. It also also necessary to align assessment requirements so that each group of students is assessed toward disciplinary learning objectives, but also has an incentive to coordinate, to collaborate, and produce artefacts that are useful for their peers in the other disciplines. Clear and constant communication among academic leaders was key to resolve any unforeseen issue and to manage students expectations. The presence of an industry engagement manager to manage the expectations and involvement of the industry partners was also seen a key success factor.
D. Groups should preferably work in isolation from other groups
Students need to learn agile methods in isolation before increasing the complexity by introducing multi-group based work, i.e. where groups share a common code base. The complexity of handling communication and technical merge conflicts seems to high, and they will start trying to form ”super-teams” to avoid this. Unfortunately this introduce overhead within each “super-team” which means to is difficult to collaborate effectively. It is, therefore, preferable to provide each team with separate problems using separate code bases.
Similarly it is also difficult to have groups working on top of work that has already been developed elsewhere unless members of the original group are present in the new. The students have a tendency to spend too much time on learning what is already there and it takes a long time before they are comfortable with developing new code or refactoring old code. It seems that beginner students are faster at learning new technologies from scratch as their own code base is developing from scratch.