Evaluating capstone project through flexible and collaborative use of Scrum framework

Abstract—Scrum framework disseminates principles that guarantee a dynamic and adaptable Software development process. Supporting the software engineering teaching using agile methodologies and Scrum framework with some proper adaptations is the challenge of Federal University of São Carlos in the Software Engineering specialization course for graduated students. The article presents an evaluation of Scrum adaptations performed to evaluate the capstone project. In this case study, the adoption of Scrum to manage the capstone project represents a direct and objective approach in order to have an environment similar to the real one. Moreover, the inexperience of the teams, the partial dedication in the projects and the distributed teams showed the necessity of self-management of the teams among other lessons learned to teach Software Engineering in this setting. Finally, evaluating a capstone project using Scrum framework in a flexible and collaborative way made it possible to realize the difficulties faced by the teams and the need for technical improvements, thanks to Scrum framework functions.

Keywords — agile methodologies, software engineering, higher education, SCRUM

I. INTRODUCTION
Software Engineering teaching needs to follow the industry demands when the purpose is to improve the skills of graduated students who seek better placements in industry or want to update knowledge to complement the graduation learning.
Developers in Software industry complain about the constant changes in software requirements. In traditional methods, the clear requirements are prerequisites to the next level. Currently, developers need to transform the constant chaos of Software development industry in advantage and find a way of better assisting the client [1]. Due to fast changes in this industry, traditional approaches are not very practical to some professionals [2].
The Software development in the industry is fast and offers our students an unstable environment in relation to the aspect of technology, requirements management and team management. The industry needs a professional who is flexible to manage all the chaos in an unstable environment and able to deliver a functional product in a short period. It is possible to conclude that there is the necessity of an approach closer to the real environment, in which theories and practices can be applied allowing the student to have a further learning using agile methodologies of Software development [2].
In face of this setting, the Federal University of São Carlos/Brazil offers a Software Engineering specialization course for web development for graduated students based on agile methodology principles. For this to be achieved, Scrum framework was chosen and the course was adapted so that the students were able to learn and, at the same time, apply Scrum principles.
Since the first group in 2003, the traditional methodology was adopted in the capstone project. However, some problems were faced during this period such as partial delivery of the project, because the complete project was developed in a single cycle and the traditional methodology was used [2]. Some studies discuss that this is an ideal methodology for inexperienced students [3]. However, the analysis of the course reality showed that some variables needed to be included such as time dedicated, experience, talent for programming and auto-management. Some of these variables were only realized in the end and reflected on the capstone project.
Agile methodologies and Scrum framework principles, mainly the iterative aspect of the production cycle for a delivery in each Sprint, were adapted in the course. All the subjects were enrolled, allowing the student to learn new programming techniques and to deliver a part of the capstone project following the Backlog, Sprint and stories.
In a general view, Scrum has some important meetings that guide the team so that the members can understand what is necessary to deliver. For example the Sprint Planning, the Daily Scrum, the Sprint Review and the Sprint Retrospective [1,8].
In Scrum, the Product Owner prioritizes and inserts in a list called Product Backlog the functionalities expected for the Software. The functionalities are presented to the team in order to have an assessment and the Sprint Planning establishes what the team will assume. During the period of stories performance, named Sprint, the teams perform the daily meeting for a daily follow-up of tasks and difficulties. In the end of the Sprint, the Sprint Review is performed, considering the delivery of what was performed during the period and after that, the Sprint Retrospective aims at identifying positive and negative points, and what can be improved [1,8,5].
During Software process development using Scrum, some artifacts are generated to give an idea of what the team needs to do. These artifacts are the following: the Sprint Backlog showing the stories contemplating desired functionalities to be implemented in the product; the Burndown charts showing the performance relation versus the stories assumed by the team; and the Backlog release that relates everything that will be delivered, which might comprise one or more Sprints. All these meetings and artifacts are inserted in the Software development process and they will guide the work [1,8].
The entire course syllabus was divided in phases that allow the students to learn gradually and release a compatible part of the capstone project based on subjects studied during the classes [2]. In order to make the academic environment closer to the real world, the students were grouped in teams of 6 to 7 people, a Technical Product Owner was named to help all the teams, and a Product Owner was chosen for each team in order to create a reality and have an impact in the learning setting.
Organizing a course with such a structure has an impact in the student ́s learning process. This way, the purpose of this paper is to determine, discuss and quantify how Scrum became flexible and collaborative when teaching Software Engineering. Adaptation and other aspects of development were evaluated with a questionnaire applied in about 34 students who were concluding the specialization course in 2013.
The paper is organized as follow: Section II shows how teams were organized during the course so that Scrum methodology could have a real application. Section III shows the outcomes and discussion about the questionnaire applied to students in the end of the last year of the course. Section IV presents the related works; Section V presents the lessons learned for this kind of application according to the student ́s point-of-view. Finally, Section VI presents the conclusion of the research.

II. ADAPTING SCRUM FOR THE SPECIALIZATION COURSE
In general, there are 30 to 40 students attending the Software Engineering specialization course per year. The course lasts 444 hours distributed over two years [2], the classes are offered twice a week and most people in the teams live in different cities, making it difficult to manage the capstone team.
During this period, since the beginning the students are grouped in small teams. According to the Scrum philosophy, small teams, not exceeding 10 people, are easier to manage [1]. Therefore, in this course, the teams are organized in 6 to 7 students who have to develop a web project based on a real problem presented by the professor responsible for the Software agile development subject.
The course coordinator and the professor look for a Product Owner that will offer a problem for each group. This action creates a solution based on real requirements raised by the teams to an alleged real client. From this moment, the teams effectively start using Scrum.
Scrum framework is transmitted to students in the first day of class and in the course of two years, the topics highlighted in the course such as Sprint Planning, Daily Scrum, Sprint Review and Sprint Retrospective are reviewed. Often, these topics are reviewed before students start using Scrum to develop the project.
The class that finished the course in the end of 2013 had 34 students grouped in five teams. Each team was responsible for a project that became a software solution for the Product Owner. The systems created during two years of course are briefly described as follow:
a) SICOM: SICOM offers control and management of properties and residents in the campus of the Federal University of São Carlos, such as identification and location for the people who live there.
b) University Restaurant System: the university restaurant system automates the stock control process reducing the time of this operation and making it easier to raise administrative and financial information.
c) Student assistance system: The student assistance system offers computational support for requests and management of scholarships handled by the University social assistance department.
d) IIS: The institutional identification system is responsible for managing the individual’s identity in the Federal University of São Carlos.
e) Property management system: the property management system aims at managing the life cycle of Federal University of São Carlos properties.
By analyzing Scrum adaptation under a general view, it is possible to report some changes in the quantity of days for a Sprint. According to the official version of Scrum, a Sprint must take 2 to 4 weeks and in the academic setting, a Sprint took about 41-84 days. This modification was an explicit order given by the course coordination because the quantity of days each Sprint must have is defined by the coordination.
Another adaptation is the definition of Scrum Master role turnover. This role turnover has allowed each student to understand the idea behind the daily meeting management, remove obstacles, protect the team from external problems and make things easier. The addition of the Scrum Master role turnover in the course promotes its use in a collaborative way.
Another challenge originated from the application of Scrum in the course is that most students have full-time jobs, and they dedicate time to the project only on weekends and free time during the week. Thus, in this course, teams reported the necessity of appealing to instant communicators such as messengers to deal with distance issues.
In the official version of Scrum, in-person daily meetings are necessary. Later on, in the academic adaption, the daily meetings were replaced by one meeting with all members through online communicators as a solution. Another resource used by students was emailing during the project. Most communication was performed through email among all the members and the Product Owner.
Another adaption was the replacement of Kanban used to present task lists through an electronic worksheet. Therefore, all artifacts necessary to manage the capstone project migrated to an online version. All the documents such as backlog, sprint backlog and burndown charts were shared by the members of the teams to promote interaction and follow-up.
The team starts applying Scrum since the first contact with the Product Owner. After the first meeting with the Product Owner, the groups raise the requirements. So, the members of the team discuss to start the creation of the Backlog. During the capstone project, the professor responsible for the agile development subject and a tutor support the team. Both have technical expertise to guide the teams in technical issues and in the Scrum.
Leite and Lucrédio’s work [5] reported the adaptation of the Scrum in the team that developed the University Restaurant System. And we verified that the same adaption was applied in other groups in the same specialization course concluded in 2013. In the article [4], Prado and Ferrari report that the distributed teams appeal to the online communicators and email. But there is a difference realized by the teams mentioned in Prado and Lucrédio works, the need of meeting in person in the end of classes to clarify some doubts concerning the development. Other topics mentioned concern the use of SVN to centralize the code and keep the files updated for all the members in all the teams.
All adaptions made by the teams helped to develop the capstone project during the two years available to define the scope, the interviews with the Product Owner and the implementation. Thus, in the end of each Sprint, the Sprint Review is performed in the presence of the professor responsible for the agile development subject and the tutor. The Product Owner is not present in all Sprint Reviews, being invited only to some of them. In this case, another adaption to the academic setting is characterized. During the Sprint Review, it was possible to control the evolution based on the implementation according to the level of difficulty of the subjects already studied. The idea is that the students deliver parts of the project based on the subjects learned.
In the beginning, as reported by Leite and Lucrédio in [5], the team faced some difficulties. In the first Sprint, the professor helped the students to define the stories to be implemented. After defining each story, students played the Planning Poker in order to determine the points of each story. Each story has a level that defines its complexity. In this phase, students felt the necessity of further knowledge about the technology to be used in order to improve the outcome of the first Sprint.
Leite and Lucrédio [5] reported all the regressions in their work. A summarized version of what is faced during the period can be seen in Table 1 with the implementation of the “Federal University of São Carlos Restaurant Management System” project. The table shows the main obstacles identified by this group, but in general, it can be extended to others.
The Sprint analyses of all teams showed all the challenges faced in this process using Scrum in a flexible and collaborative way. Reviewing the Burndown chart of each
Sprint developed by all the teams, it is possible to realize the evolution during these two years studying new technologies and working on the the capstone project. The idea of using the Burndown chart for follow-up is because the chart shows how many tasks are performed by a team during a period. In this case, the period reported in the chart is the time of each Sprint.
TABLE I. GENERAL VIEW OF SPRINT – TABLE ADAPTED FROM [5]
 Sprint Days Stories
Obstacles
Project Scope.
Lack of planning in the meetings.
Complications in the self-managing model.
Technical issues.
Outdated documentation.
Lack of dedication from the member of the project. Overload of programming activities.
 1 41 2 71
3 56
4 84 5 63
4 8
4
4 5
     6 63 10
 7 55
12


It is possible to highlight a team among the followed-up teams, for example, the team reported by Leite and Lucrédio. Figure 1 shows the main point of the team evolution. In the first and fourth Sprint, this team suffered some regressions causing delays in the tasks. In the fourth Sprint, a lack of commitment with Scrum practices was reported due to the amount of overwork. This episode generated a lack of trust in the real situation of the project in the Sprint causing a delay in the activities; and it was reported that some tasks were not accomplished [5].
However, the team showed a significant improvement in Sprint 7 thanks to an experienced Scrum Master that is always vehemently following the framework principles and characteristics according to Leite and Lucrédio[5]. In the last Sprint, the team showed more maturity in the development process and dealt better with the regressions. This was verified in all the other teams too. Thus, the outcome of Sprint 7 in Leite and Lucrédio ́s team showed that all tasks were performed, except one that was not concluded because there was a disagreement concerning the operation flow.
In general, in the end of the project, the teams realized that if everybody dedicated more and lined up with the goals, the outcome of each Sprint could be much better, as mentioned in work [5].
The flexible and collaborative use of Scrum applied in the capstone project provoked some changes in the learning process of these students. Students worked on the capstone project during the two years and delivered it in parts due to the Sprints. An important aspect using an approach based on Scrum is how much it helped the students in the learning process and what were the lessons learned with this experience from the students’ point of view. The experience reported by Leite and Lucrédio can similarly describe other teams ́ behavior. However, in order to obtain an opinion and evaluate the approach, a questionnaire was applied for each student based on his or her own experience developing the capstone project.

III. EVALUATING THE ADOPTION OF SCRUM
In order to evaluate the impact of the Scrum-based approach in the class of 34 students who concluded the specialization course in 2013, a questionnaire was sent by email to all the students. After the end of the period of collection, all the answers were summarized and analyzed. The questionnaire considered a view of students’ profile, how the team used Scrum, the positive and negative aspects when using Scrum and if the student knew the Scrum
The questionnaire was composed of nine questions, with five objective questions and four open-response questions. In all objective questions it was possible to define a percentage and assess the maximum and minimum value. In the open- response questions it was necessary to summarize the main ideas in the answers and group them to have a better analysis. Therefore, it was possible to quantify more precisely the students ́opinion about the use of Scrum adaptations in the capstone project.
The questionnaire sent to the students was composed of the following questions:
a) Do the members of the team have any knowledge about Scrum?
b) Arethemembersoftheteamfromthesamecity?
c) HowoftendoestheSprintPlanninghappen?
d) HowwastheSprintPlanningperformed?
e) HowdidtheteamadapttheScrumforthecapstoneproject?
f) What are the positive points of Scrum in the project?
g) What are the negative points of Scrum adaptations in the Project during the course?
h) Didthepreviousknowledgecontributefortheproject?
i) Do you use Scrum in other settings besides the Software development one?
The answers from each student were summarized and
discussed. In the following summary, the students’ profile, the Scrum adaptations by the team, the positive aspects using Scrum and the negative aspects using Scrum adaptations are initially related.

A. Student ́sProfile
The specialization course is offered twice a week and most students are from cities near São Carlos, which is located in the countryside of São Paulo state in Brazil, or from the capital. Therefore, 100% of the students do not live in the same city where the members of the team live, and the teams were composed of members from different cities characterizing distributed teams without full dedication to the project.
Another point observed with the questionnaire is that not all the students know Scrum framework. In total, only 29% of the members knew it. This contributed to create a setting where the students had no knowledge about agile methodologies, generating new challenges for the course.
As the questionnaire was applied in the end of the specialization course, it was possible to quantify if the previous knowledge in programming or any other technical knowledge helped the user in the project. In general, 94% of the students reported that the previous knowledge contributed to the capstone project. This result might be related to the type of course. With regard to a specialization course, some prerequisites are demanded before the student gets in. Thus, the more the student is prepared, the more it will help him during the activities, even in the capstone project.
Other issues define if the student uses Scrum in other setting besides the Software development one. It can sound conflicting, because only 47% claim that use Scrum in different settings and 71% claim that they do not know Scrum.
It is possible to relate the 47% of students to the setting where they work. In some reports, they mention that they use Scrum in the bank office, in the production process control, in the development of games and even in the Software development setting. Maybe the 71% is related to the further knowledge of Scrum, because living the routine where the Scrum is applied is different from having a further understanding about the framework.
The profile of students were mapped using questions (a), (b), (h) and (i). All results showed that the 34 students came from different cities, only 29% of the students knew Scrum and 71% of the students did not know Scrum. Most students (94%) mentioned that the previous knowledge in programming language and Scrum contributed to the project and 41% of the students used Scrum in another setting.

B. Scrum adaptations
Adaptations were necessary because the teams need to develop the capstone project in a distributed way and the responsibility for the Project needs to be shared. However, the use of Scrum demands intensive contact among the teams. Thus, it was necessary to adapt mainly the Kanban and the meetings that provide a closer follow-up. In order to apply Scrum in an academic version, students had to take some actions such as replacing the board containing the stories and tasks of a Sprint by digital resources and using the online communication to keep the Sprints in progress.
In general, all the students combined the online communication, email exchange and in-person meetings to perform the Sprint Planning. Therefore, in 65% of times, the use of instant communicators and e-mails were more frequent than the in-person meetings. Only 26% used all the options to perform the Sprint Planning, as presented in Figure 2.
For a better understanding, the Sprint Planning is a meeting in the Scrum that defines what is necessary to do in that Sprint based on what is available on the top of the Product Backlog. In the official version, the Sprint Planning is performed with the Product Owner. In this case, it was not possible to have the Product Owner always available, so the meetings were organized online most of the time, as presented in Figure 2. The outcome of this meeting is that the students need to implement during the Sprint. In general, the Sprint Planning is performed in the beginning of a Sprint to define and understand the tasks.
Sprint Planning frequency varies from team to team. The rule is that the team has a date to initiate a Sprint and a deadline to deliver a functional part in the same Sprint. The Sprint planning time increased twice a month (18% of the team), weekly (41% of the team) or monthly (38% of the team). Only 3% of the students did not know how to answer this question, as presented in Figure 2.
The Sprint Planning do not replace daily meetings, aims at planning the Sprint and must be performed primarily always in the beginning of a Sprint. However, the distance and the lack of time make the students create a strategy that allows a closer follow-up with monthly, weekly or bimonthly meetings. In order to complete the Scrum adaptation in the capstone project, the answer to question (e) was analyzed. Therefore, a brief description of the students’ answers is shown as follow.
It was interesting to analyze the students’ answers because it was possible to note the Scrum potential. As a framework, Scrum provides an idea of how it can be used. Therefore, the main concern of students was keeping the communication to guarantee a good project. Some students, almost 32%, reported that used the online communicators to have a daily meeting; and to reduce their distance; they also exchanged emails. In general, the students told that they arranged weekly meetings with online communicators to have information about the Project development.
Almost 18% of the students reported that they inserted the Product Backlog, Sprint Backlog and Burndown in web tools to share the content with some members, allowing the online follow-up. Some students told that the in-person meetings were held mainly in the retrospectives and in planning meetings. Other students commented that in the end of the classes they used to meet to discuss the evolution of the project. Other students reported the creation of long-term Sprints, and other students addressed the tasks according to the technical ability of each member. Eventually, other students told that when they finished the task, they used to help others who had not finished yet.
By analyzing question (e), some students, about 24%, did not give an opinion about Scrum adaptation performed in their teams. Almost 12% of the students told that using Scrum was difficult in the beginning and two students from this group reported that the problem was in the difficulty of communication.

C. Negative aspects of using Scrum adaption.
Students are free to adapt some framework points such as communication and follow-up. All the changes can have a negative impact based on the options defined by each team. To have a better understanding about the impact of adaptations, the answers to question (g) were analyzed. All the answers were analyzed and the main idea was summarized and grouped for a complete understanding of the impact. A brief description is presented as follow.
By analyzing the questionnaire, it was possible to conclude that the flexibility and collaborative use of Scrum represents a challenge of 41% of the student in the agile methodology learning process. Although the flexible use guaranteed the adoption of the framework by the course and by the teams, the mapping shows some negative aspects in Scrum adaptation.
About 6% of the students considered that replacing the in- person meetings by virtual meetings contributed to the negligence on the part of some members in the team; 6% of the students considered that learning with the project management was more demanding; 6% of the students considered the lack of dedication from the members a problem; 12% of the students faced difficulties in following Scrum in a distributed format and 9% of the students considered that the lack of experience with the Scrum caused some regression.
The remaining 18% of the students did not comment on the negative aspect of adaptation and only 3% did not identified problems with the respective teams using Scrum adaptations.
Considering all the percentages, it is possible to infer that the use of Scrum in the capstone project caused a change of attitude from the students. The use of this framework clearly showed the members that really participated and others that did not show interest. Therefore, in the end, a member draws the attention of other uninterested members to be more participative, or in some situations, this members give up.
The capstone project became demanding for only 6%, but the advantages of living in an academic area similar to the professional area is reassuring. On the other hand, the capstone project is made in parts, making it easier to follow the evolution of the project.

D. Positive Aspects of using Scrum.
Besides the negative aspects raised in this questionnaire, the positive aspects of using Scrum were identified. The good news is that the positive aspect of this approach justifies the management of the capstone project development using Scrum. In order to analyze the positive aspects of adopting Scrum, the answers for question (f) were summarized and a brief description is presented as follow.
In the evaluation, all the students who answered the question reported that the use of Scrum stimulates the participation of all the members of the team and helps to release functional products in a faster way, adding more agility to the team. This agility provides a continuous improvement in Software delivery, because at the end of each Sprint it is possible to receive a feedback, make more changes and understand better the product.
The students appreciated this approach because with a minimum view of project it is possible to start the implementation and gradually understand the new requirements. In addition, the flexibility in using the framework provides a different way of working, for example: working remotely. The students say that the use of online spreadsheets makes it easier to understand the status of the Project and defines the user who is performing the task.
A student said that using Scrum in this format provides a more real framework setting, which is truly used in the industry. Another student reported that it is possible to use all the twelve principles of the agile methodology with this approach.
In a general view, the students told that the use of Scrum provides an agile setting, continuous feedback, frequent deliveries, less bugs, more motivated team, improvements in organization, clear delegation of tasks, the possibility of focusing on a product functionality, a better view of the Project development and improvement in the communication. These improvements increase the interaction and participation of the members in the team.
According to the percentage summary, around 18% of the students told that this approach increases the speed in delivery of some functional parts of the project; 18% of the students agree that it increases the participation of the members; 15% of the students told that it is easier to manage the project when they face adversities; 3% of the students told that it is possible to use a framework used in the market in practice; 6% of the students told that the use of Scrum allows a continuous improvement; 29% of the students told that it is easier to manage the project using Scrum; and 3% of the students told that it is possible to use principles of agile methods.

V. LESSONS LEARNED
The evaluation showed that the approach is valid when analyzing the positive aspects in relation to the negative aspects. According to the students’ point-of-view, the flexible and collaborative use of Scrum increases the communication, feedback, continuous improvement and provide faster deliveries compared to the traditional model. In other words, students see the outcomes from their work in a faster and gradually way when compared to the traditional models to perform the capstone project.
According to Leite and Lucrédio [5], it is understandable that the adoption of a framework like Scrum will provide the self-management of the members. The students need to take responsibility for what they need to deliver. This practice is sometimes different from what the students face in some organizations, when they receive a work and are constantly charged for faster deliveries. In Scrum, the team needs to work together and cooperate to reach a goal. In their work [5], Leite and Lucrédio report this kind of experience, and they add that it is important to define clear purposes, the roles and the tools.
Other lessons learned in Leite and Lucrédio’s work [5], and which can be extended to the teams that concluded the capstone project in the end of 2013 are the following: the communication is an essential tool; defining points to be discussed in meetings is a good methodology to improve the efficiency; identifying the limitation and trying a solution for the next iteration are great techniques; sharing knowledge among the members and tutors; omitting the use of Scrum in
some period of the project can cause delays; and the commitment and shared knowledge provide positive outcomes.

VI. CONCLUSION
The article proposes to determine, discuss and quantify how Scrum becomes flexible and collaborative in Software Engineering teaching. It presents a general view of the specialization course offered in São Carlos, in the state of São Paulo/Brazil focused on web development. Next, the way the course allows the flexible and collaborative use of Scrum to teach Software engineering is presented. In order to evaluate the impact of this approach, a questionnaire was sent to the students who finished the course in the end of 2013.
Considering the students’ point-of-view, the approach allows to improve the experience in the capstone project development. Adaptations performed by students taking into account the flexibility, communication and releasing of functional parts of the system are important points.
Finally, using Scrum during the capstone project helps the professor to see the difficulty, guide the student as best as they can and provide assistance to the team with big difficulties during the project development. With this approach, it is possible to create points of action to try to reduce problems related to delivery.